<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Baʻal-samz] or, Soveraigne balsome, gently applied in a few weighty considerations (by way of quærie) for healing the distempers of such professors of religion as Satan hath wounded and drawn aside (under the notion of living in God) to the utter renouncing and casting off the use of divine ordinances, and Gospel-institutions of worship. With an apendix by way of postscript to such professors, wherein the most principall grounds upon which they build their practise, are fully answered and removed. And a catalogue of the errors that many of them hold since they left the ordinances, discovered. As also a true relation of Gods extraordinary working upon one of this way very lately in Plimouth, to the sight of his error, for the good of others published. / By Will. Bartlet, an unworthy minister of the Gospel, and lecturer at Bytheford in Devonshire.</title>
            <author>Bartlet, William, 1609 or 10-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 221 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E549_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868030</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868030</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165014</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165014)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 85:E549[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Baʻal-samz] or, Soveraigne balsome, gently applied in a few weighty considerations (by way of quærie) for healing the distempers of such professors of religion as Satan hath wounded and drawn aside (under the notion of living in God) to the utter renouncing and casting off the use of divine ordinances, and Gospel-institutions of worship. With an apendix by way of postscript to such professors, wherein the most principall grounds upon which they build their practise, are fully answered and removed. And a catalogue of the errors that many of them hold since they left the ordinances, discovered. As also a true relation of Gods extraordinary working upon one of this way very lately in Plimouth, to the sight of his error, for the good of others published. / By Will. Bartlet, an unworthy minister of the Gospel, and lecturer at Bytheford in Devonshire.</title>
                  <author>Bartlet, William, 1609 or 10-1682.</author>
                  <author>M. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 62, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by G. Dawson, for Elizabeth Overton in Popes-head Alley, neere the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in xylographic Hebrew characters.</note>
                  <note>The last three leaves contain "A catalogue of those (never enough to be abhorred opinions)", and "A true copy of a letter from Plimouth, February the 12" signed: M.P.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 5th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165014:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> OR, Soveraigne Balſome, Gently applied in a few weighty Conſiderations (by way of <hi>Quaerie</hi>) for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the diſtempers of ſuch Profeſſors of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as Satan hath wounded and drawn aſide (under the Notion of living in God) to the utter renouncing and caſting off the uſe of Divine Ordinances, and Goſpel-Inſtitutions of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>With an Apendix by way of Poſtſcript to ſuch Profeſſors, wherein the moſt principall grounds upon which they build their practiſe, are fully anſwered and removed.</p>
            <p>And a Catalogue of the errors that many of them hold ſince they left the Ordinances, diſcovered. As alſo a true Relation of Gods extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary working upon one of this way very lately in <hi>Plimouth,</hi> to the ſight of his error, for the good of others publiſhed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Will. Bartlet,</hi> an unworthy Miniſter of the Goſpel, and Lecturer at <hi>Bytheford</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Even from the dayes of your Fathers yee are gone away from my Ordinances, and have not kept them: Return unto me, and I will return unto you, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, &amp;c. <bibl>
                  <hi>MAL. 3.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Is there no Balm in Gilead? Is there no Phyſitian there? Why there is not the health of the daughter of my people recovered? <bibl>
                  <hi>JER. 8.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Brethren, if any of you doe erre from the truth, and one convert him; let him know that he which converteth the ſinner from the error of his way, ſhall ſave a ſoule from death, and ſhall hide a multitude of ſinnes. <bibl>
                  <hi>IAM. 5.19, 20.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>G. Dawſon,</hi> for <hi>Elizabeth Overton</hi> in Popes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head Alley, neere the Royall Exchange. 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:165014:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:165014:2"/>
            <head>TO ALL THE CORDIALL Friends, and ſincere lovers of the Lord IESUS and his SYON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>PRETIOUS SOULES,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>EE cannot be ignorant how the propheſies of old,<note n="a" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.1 ad 10. 2 Pet. 2. per tot. 1 Joh. 2.18.22. Jude 4. ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. Matth. 24, 24, 25, &amp;c.</note> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt; yea by Chriſt himſelf, concerning the perilouſneſſe of the laſt dayes, in reſpect of the evils both of opinion and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, that ſhould bee broached and embraced by all ſorts of people in them; are now in our times abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly fulfilled; wherein there is as much difference, and as great variety, (if not greater) betweene men in their opinions, as there is between them in
<pb facs="tcp:165014:3"/>their faſhions, which I finde to be<note n="b" place="margin">Sic etiam in cunctis Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genis, tanta ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtium varietas &amp; aſperitatis multiformitas inolevit ut neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius generis paenè quilibes cenſcatur, ex qua re bene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetavit tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Regis <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theldredi, &amp;c. Anony.</hi>
               </note> propheſied of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, many hundred years ſince, touching <hi>England:</hi> and like as mens faſhions in their apparrell, diet, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, are ſome of them more monſtrous, odious and loathſome then others; ſo are their opinions in Religion, and matters of Doctrine and Worſhip: and ſo blaſphemous, abominable, and damnable, are ſome opinions and practices now in <hi>England,</hi> as that nothing but the patience of an infinite God could poſsibly ſuffer them to have any longer a Being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us. How were the Churches of Chriſt weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and endangered by ſuch <hi>Peſts</hi> in the Primitive times? What a many<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Antichriſts were there then? 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.18. What a many falſe Chriſts, falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, falſe Prophets and Teachers, ſelfe-lovers. Sin-lovers, and lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God, going up and down deceiving poore ſouls, eſpecially poore ſilly women, that were alwayes learning, but never came to the knowledge of the Truth, 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 3.6. who were not onely reſiſters, but ſubverters of the faith delivered once to the Saints, <hi>Jude</hi> 3.4. And is it not ſo at this day? Are nor the Churches of Chriſt as much poſered and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered now through ſuch falſe Chriſts, falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, falſe Teachers, &amp;c. meere Antichriſts, that have a forme of godlineſſe, but deny the power thereof. The Lord Jeſus (the great Shepheard of his ſheep, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.20.) hath but newly recovered his poore afflicted weather-beaten Lambes, from bloody Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valeriſme, tyranny and oppreſsion, but forthwith their ſouls are aſſaulted with<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Beza</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates it Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all malices, the words are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſpiritualneſſe of evill and wickedneſſe; carnall wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are inferiour to ſpirituall, which ocupieth the higheſt part of the Soule, &amp;c. and are not laid out in carnall paſſions and concupiſcences, &amp;c. <hi>Lawr. Com. and Warre with Angels. p. 5.</hi>
               </note> ſpiritual wickedneſſes
<pb facs="tcp:165014:3"/>in high places, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12. Some read it, <hi>In high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> but I ſuppoſe it may be read better, <hi>in heavenly places,</hi> or <hi>things,</hi> as<note n="e" place="margin">The word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in ſublimi, <hi>ſaith Beza,</hi> but it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies heavenly, as in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of your Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, which may have relation to things as pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and then it ſhews the things about which his malicious ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, that is, to take all heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things from us, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of whatſoever is heavenly. <hi>id. ib.</hi>
               </note> ſome obſerve on the place. If the differences amongſt us, touching mens opinions and practiſes, were onely about ſuch things as are not much materiall, or were not at all determined in the Scripture, or after ſuch a manner as is dubious not onely to particular perſons, but whole Churches of Chriſt, the matter were not great; for God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly wiſe herein, and in my weake apprehenſion, hath left theſe things ſo, that thereby there might be occaſion given the more to exerciſe our Charity, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Humility one towards another. But when they ſhall grow to ſuch a height, as to call into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion fundamentall truths, and not ſo much to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, as flatly to deny them, and to pluck up the foundation it ſelf; then 'tis high time for us to look about, &amp; not only to hold faſt, that no man take our Crown, but to<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>i.</hi> ut fitis propugnatores fidei. <hi>uti Hen. Steph. in verb.</hi>
               </note> contend for the faith once delivered to the Saints, <hi>Jude</hi> 3. And is it not thus with us at this<note n="g" place="margin">Who can num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the duſt of Atheiſts, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Hereticks, Hypocrites, or meaſure the ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Globe of meere Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, or ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates? <hi>Barl.</hi>
               </note> day? Don't we ſee that men are not aſhamed to write and ſpeake againſt the Divinity of Chriſt, and the Scriptures, againſt the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt; yea, how they deny the Trinity, and plead for theſe very abominations that are (without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie) odious and loathſome both to God and good Men<note n="h" place="margin">A catalogue of ſome of which abominable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors held by ſuch as caſt off the uſe of ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces you ſhall find ſet down in the end of the Book.</note>. Now concerning errors in Doctrine, I have not ſo directly to deale with, in the following Diſcourſe (though my ſoule bleeds to conſider the diſhonour comes to the Lord Jeſus by them,) but thoſe which more eſpecially concerne Worſhip, and not every petty error here neither, but the grand and capitall one, and that wherein I judge all error of Doctrine and Apoſtaſie at laſt to terminate, <hi>viz.</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:165014:4"/>Renouncing and caſting off, of all Duties and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, or Inſtitutions of Divine Worſhip, ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Chriſt himſelfe to be obſerved in the dayes of the New Teſtament; unchurching the right conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Congregations and Aſſemblies of <hi>Syon,</hi> dna plucking up the publick Miniſtery of the Goſpel by the roots, and this not ſo much in ſome reſpect (as thoſe that are called <hi>Seekers,</hi> who deny publick Churches, Miniſtery, &amp;c. for want of Apoſtles, and other like extraordinary gifted men to adminiſter, &amp;c.) but abſolutely looking on the performance of Duties, and uſe of Ordinances, Miniſtery and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as poore, low, weake Diſpenſations, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh things, not fit for ſuch as live in God to ſtoop ſo low, as to make uſe of. And ſo under a pretence of living in God, they teach poore, weake ſoules, that there is a life to be attained unto, wherein they may live<note n="i" place="margin">That there is a life to be obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers here on earth, that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is not deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But that this life is without ordinances alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, when they may enjoy the uſe of them, and that puts them neceſſarily upon the renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and caſting them off, is that which we flatly deny, as being contrary not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the ſacred Scriptures, but experience of the ſoundeſt Chriſtians, as I have ſhewed in the following Diſcourſe.</note> 
               <hi>without</hi> the uſe of Ordinances, or perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of Duties, <hi>without</hi> obſervation of the Lords day, or <hi>Sabbath, without</hi> Church-fellowſhip, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> inſtructing their children in the knowledge of the Scriptures, <hi>without</hi> craving a bleſsing on the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture when they make uſe of it, or returning thankes for it. And that which is moſt abominable, that they may attain and enjoy ſuch a liberty, as to be under no law, but that of the Spirit, as they ſay, and ſo may perpetrate any impiety, without controll, or check of God or Man; for they live in God alone, and ſo are above all things here below: &amp; ſo would make a perſons living in God, &amp; living in the practice of ſin, to conſiſt &amp; ſtand together. Theſe are the men that the following Diſcourſe concernes, and whom I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but look on (eſpecially thoſe of them that out of a profeſſed judgement, and fixed ſelfe-will, doe in a
<pb facs="tcp:165014:4"/>high and peremptory manner proceed in their way) as the dangerous peſts that can be, both to the State, as well as to Religion; for take away true Chriſtian Religion, or the true worſhip of God, and power of godlineſſe out of a State, or Common-wealth, and what do you therein but as it were take the ſoul from the body: For what is the ſincere practiſe of ſound Religion and godlineſſe in a State, but<note n="k" place="margin">There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in a true Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth that can onely direct it ſelf to the benefit of State onely, but that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt bee alſo reſpected, the care of State being but the By, and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the main of every Chriſtian intendment. And ther fore oftentimes even in thoſe things which ſeem moſt properly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the State, is Religion in them moſt regarded; the care of State in reſpect of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, being like the care of our bodies, for which holy men care, but ſo only as for the houſes of their ſoules. &amp;c. <hi>Levers Hiſtory of the Defend of the Cath Faith.</hi>
               </note> the life and ſoule of it? Let that be once neglected, corrupted, or extirpated, and the other cannot long ſtand after; and when is Religion deſtroyed, but when we make it to patronize impiety. And hence it is that ſuch as are guilty of the forementioned abomination, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing Ordinances, &amp;c. are ſo frequently deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by ſuch Epithites as ſhew nothing but confuſion and deſtruction to betide thoſe places and perſons where they are entertained and countenanced. It is ſufficient in this place, (having ſpoken more largely hereof in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion of the Appendix) to ſhew you that the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> calls them<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Pet. 3.17.</hi> Leſt ye be led away with the error <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ſo in chap. <hi>2.7,</hi> &amp;c, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> dicuntur homines qui volunt eſſe fine lege, qui emnia legum repagula perfringunt, ab <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, quod legem praeſertim drvinam ſignificat, homines qui nec jus nec fas curant &amp;c. <hi>Ger in loc.</hi> vocat <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> quos prius <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> oſtendit, hos, nullo jure, nullis ne legibus poſſe in ordine retineri, ſed perumpunt omnia jura: quid vis enim ſibi licere putant, Scripturaſque ſibi ſubjiciunt. Horum exemplum valdè eſt pernicioſum etiam piis, ideo cavendum, ne horum erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus abrepti, veritatem fidei amittant. <hi>Aret. in loc. ut ſupra.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which <hi>Lori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and other more ſound Interpreters doe tranſlate, <hi>ex-leges,</hi> or <hi>lawleſſe Libertines,</hi> ſuch as under a pretence of Chriſtian liberty, allow themſelves in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of all manner of ſenſuall luſts, to the diſgrace and ſcandall of the Goſpel; for through their occaſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on <hi>the way of truth is evill ſpoken of,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. Yet whiles I am oppoſing the opinion and practice of ſuch <hi>New,</hi> though no <hi>True</hi> Goſpellers, &amp;c. I would not have ye
<pb facs="tcp:165014:5"/>(the pretious ſervants of God, that <hi>keep his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements,</hi> and the <hi>Teſtimony of Jeſus, Rev.</hi> 12.17.) to conceive that I doe in the leaſt goe about to plead for any ordinances or worſhip of mans invention, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; for falſe ordinances and worſhip that are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in <hi>Antichriſts</hi> ſhop, and beare no other ſtamp upon them then the Image of humane Authority: For I know as it's all one to<note n="m" place="margin">Lever ut ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra, p. 366.</note> deny God and to deny his Service; ſo I do latry is as wel in falſe worſhip as in no worſhip: &amp; I am aſſured that Ordinances of divine <hi>worſhip</hi> that are of mans making though never ſo wiſe or great, are no plants of Gods. planting, neither doth he accept of them, or of thoſe that make uſe of them, but<note n="n" place="margin">Matth. 15.8, 9-13. Col. 2.20, 21, 22, 23, 24. Ezek. 20.39.</note> lookes on them as vain worſhippers and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhipers, polluters &amp; prophaners of his glorious &amp; reverend Name. Or (2.) that I allowed of theuſe of true ordinances and worſhip that Chriſt himſelfe hath inſtituted and commanded, in a falſe way, or contrary to the right order which Chriſt hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to his people in the Goſpel, and was in uſe in the primitive and Apoſtolicall times for our exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>Society</hi> and <hi>Combination</hi> of Saints in which (for the moſt part) they ſubſiſt properly, and are to be performed, as I have at large ſhewed in another<note n="o" place="margin">Modell of the Congregational way, where this matter is fully handled and cleared in the two firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> place: For I know that the ſame God that hath called his people to worſhip him, doth require them to take the ſame way and order he hath<note n="p" place="margin">As God hath not left it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and worſhipped, or not, ſo he hath not left people at their own liberty to worſhip him how and in what manner they pleaſe, or as it ſeemeth good in their own eyes, but hath given forth a Rule and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be obſerved by his people under the new Teſtament, as be did under the Old; which order of Gods worſhip is beſt diſcerned in the practice of the Saints in the Primitive and Apoſtolical times, ſet forth in the new Teſtament. That men might not prevaricate or alter the form of Gods ſervice, hath God himſelfe preſcribed us a preciſe form, how and in what form (or manner) we ſhould ſerve him, damning all diverſity to this his own order, wherewith he is onely pleaſed, and wherewith he is alwayes pleaſed. <hi>Levers Hiſtory of the Defend of the Cath. Faith.</hi>
               </note> preſcribed
<pb facs="tcp:165014:5"/>them, or elſe they may not expect acceptation with him, but rather reproofe from him, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.29, 40. eſpecially after he hath made known his m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in unto us and given us pretious helps for diſcovery that way, according to <hi>Acts</hi> 17 30. Neither is it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for us to ſay, that much good is done to poore ſoules by the uſe of Gods ordinances, though not performed in that way God hath appointed: For doubtleſſe however God is all ſufficient to worke good from our evill, yet we our ſelves can have but little credit or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort in it, ſeeing <hi>we take not Gods way to do his work.</hi> And if <hi>David,</hi> and other of the ſervants of God under the Law, apprehended wrath from God, and occaſion of humiliation to themſelves, for not ſeeking or ſerving of him after the due order hee had preſcribed them, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13. how much more may ſuch expect diſpleaſure from God, that now in this cleare Sunſhine of the Goſpel neglect or refuſe to ſeek and ſerve him as he hath required them by Ieſus Chriſt; but continue to adminiſter the holy things of Gods houſe (whether out of prejudice to the Congregational way, or from looking ſo much to the examples of men like themſelves or out of ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh feare what will become of them, I know not) in a moſt confuſed and diſorderly way and manner, to and amongſt drunkards, ſwearers, perſecuters, ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and moſt prophane ignorant people, that ought to be driven from, not admitted to Church-privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, never making a ſeparation between the clean and unclean, the holy and prophane: like thoſe Prieſts in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> dayes, for which the Lord was ſo much<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and learned Lectures of Mr. W. Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nill on the five firſt chapters of Ezekiel, where he abundantly holds this forth, but eſpecially p. <hi>453, 454.</hi>
               </note> diſpleaſed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.26. Or 3<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>, that I would have thoſe that enjoy the ordinances of Chriſt in a right way and order of the Goſpel, to make a
<pb facs="tcp:165014:6"/>God or Saviour of them, to place their happineſſe in them, and make them the reſting place of their hearts, or the center into which the lines of their pretious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ſhould run, or aſcribe to them any ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or power of their own to conferre grace; for this were to idolize ordinances with the Papiſts, and give them the honour is due to<note n="r" place="margin">It's not our ſtirring up our graces, opening our hearts, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth our ſelves to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, that will make an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance effectuall without Chriſt, it's he muſt doe the deed, as <hi>Ioh. 15.5</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Paul</hi> may plant, but there is no rooting of thoſe plants but by Chriſt, <hi>Apollos</hi> may water, but no growth nor increaſe but by Chriſt, <hi>1 Cor. 3.6. Id. ut ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra. p 294.</hi> When the hand of the Lord is upon an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, &amp; upon a man in that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, then there is good gotten, and then doth the ſoule gain, <hi>2 Cor. 10.4</hi> our wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons are mighty through God. <hi>p. 60.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt alone; as if ordinances had died for us, and redeemed us from hell, and purchaſed life and ſalvation at the hands of God for us, &amp; were now a pleading our cauſe for us in heaven, and making inte ceſſion to the Father in our behalfes, &amp; had received power to conquer our corruptions, eaſe our burthens, ſupply our wants, perfect our graces, &amp;c. when the contrary is moſt cleare and evident; and therefore as thoſe that caſt off the uſe of ordinances altogether, do run into the extream on the left hand, ſo doe thoſe people run into the other extream on the right hand, of truſting in ordinances, and placing their righteouſneſſe in the meere obſerving of them. And thus the Lord Ieſus Chriſt (our alone pretious Redeemer) is to this day, as of old, crucified between theſe two Thieves, of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying him in his ordinances, by a totall renouncing them, or d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wn-right idolizing them, by placing their righteouſneſſe in them. And therefore (pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſoules) while I am condemning the one my deſire is, you would not conceive me in the leaſt to plead for, or countenance the other. But my deſire and ſcope in what is done in the following diſcourſe, is to preſſe them that profeſſe Chriſt, and ſubjection to his Goſpel, to keep the <hi>Golden Mean,</hi> and to avoyd both theſe Rockes, of lifting too high, or caſting down too low, the ſacred Inſtitutions &amp; Ordinances of worſhip, which the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Head
<pb facs="tcp:165014:6"/>and King of <hi>Syon,</hi> hath appointed his Churches in all ages to make uſe of: And hee who is the great Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of hearts, and diſcerner of the reines, knowes, I have had nothing elſe in my eye, in order to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and his peoples welfare, but this alone. Now for the Work it ſelfe, I could have wiſht it in the hands of ſome of the Lords <hi>Worthies,</hi> that are farre my ſuperiours every way, and might poſſibly have done it more fully and accuratly then I have; however, ſeeing it is the Lords pleaſure to call me, and goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me in it, I cannot but follow him; and who knowes what the <hi>Strong God</hi> may doe by<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Mr. Marſhals</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on Pſalm. <hi>8.2.</hi> called, A two edged Sword out of the mouth of Babes.</note> 
               <hi>weak means?</hi> Poore <hi>David</hi> whoſe heart was upright with God, and ſought his glory in what he enterpriſed, did more with a <hi>Sling and a Stone in the Name of the Lord,</hi> againſt <hi>Goliah,</hi> that defied the <hi>Heaſt of the living God,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. then <hi>Saul</hi> with all his valiant <hi>warriours</hi> poſſibly could. 'Twas not <hi>Sauls Armour</hi> could procure <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> and therefore he throwes it from him, and goes to the work of God in Gods way. Happy ſoules that have learn'd that Art, and know how to ſet about the Lords work with the Lords Tooles; ſuch may be ſure with <hi>David,</hi> to find a proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous gale to attend them, &amp; much bleſſed ſucceſſe to follow their <hi>honeſt endeavours.</hi> Wherfore to trouble you no longer (dearly beloved) but craving your candid <hi>Interpretation</hi> of, and <hi>earneſt ſupplication</hi> for a bleſſing on the preſent work, and that in order to the <hi>eſtabliſhing of your own ſouls,</hi> and the <hi>recovering thoſe that are gone aſtray from the paths of peace and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> I leave your pretious ſouls in the arms of him, who never leaveth his, even the <hi>God of all grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> 
               <hi>who hath called us into his glory by Chriſt Jeſus, who (after yee
<pb facs="tcp:165014:7"/>have ſuffered a while) make you perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, ſettle you.</hi> In whom I deſire and truſt for ever to be found</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your and the Churches unfained Friend and Servant, <hi>W. BARTLET.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>March</hi> 1. 1648</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Courteous Reader, you are deſired, in reſpect of the Authors abſence, and great diſtance from the Preſſe, to mend with your Pen, or in love to paſſe by ſuch faults as theſe which have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Title,</hi> Balm for the Bruiſed, <hi>read</hi> A Soveraigne Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for the wounded. <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. <hi>marg.d</hi> 
               <hi>r. obſervandum. P.</hi> 3. <hi>marg.n</hi>. <hi>r. in nova Eccleſia, &amp;c. p.</hi> 4. <hi>marg.ſ</hi> 
               <hi>for Apoſtolis r. Apoſtolos. p.</hi> 9. <hi>margh</hi> 
               <hi>for</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>r.</hi> Miſtreſſe Avery. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>marg. for</hi> Id. ibid. <hi>r.</hi> Muſc. in loc. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>l,</hi> 17. <hi>r.</hi> inexpreſſible. <hi>p.</hi> 33. <hi>mar. for worſhip r. walking,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165014:7"/>
            <head>BALM for the BRVISED.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaerie</hi> I.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET it be <hi>conſidered</hi> in the <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> whether the <hi>ſacred</hi> Scriptures, commonly called the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> conſiſting of the writings of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Apoſtles, in the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that were holy men of God, and<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> vulg. red. iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirati, vel <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſed Graecum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè ſig. acti &amp; impulſi. Spiritus ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus erat Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, Prophetae e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ejus cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi, quibus Spir. S. ſcribenda dictabat. <hi>Cypr.</hi> Ergo Script. ſac. eſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ac in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibile Dei verbum. <hi>Gro.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>inſpired</hi> infallibly by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> in the compoſing of them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20, 21. be not the onely <hi>viſible</hi> Rule and<note n="b" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is taken from Architects, who in building Houſes, doe uſe a Rule, or Square, by which all the parts are carried ou with a due proportion: ſo thoſe that Chriſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployeth to build his Church, are to meaſure all matters of doctrine and worſhip by the Rule and Square of the Scriptures.</note> 
               <hi>Canon,</hi> ſo called, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. by which perſons (profeſſing the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and faith in Chriſt) are to <hi>ſquare</hi> and <hi>regulate</hi> themſelves in all matters of Doctrine and Worſhip? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the beſt and next way to come to the right knowledge of the minde of Chriſt in theſe things, be not to<note n="c" place="bottom">Nihil in Eccleſia ſonare debet niſi eloquia Dei, juxta <hi>1 Pet. 4.11.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>vid. Ger. in loc.</hi> Omne quod loquimur debemus affirmare de ſacris Scripturis, <hi>Hier. in Pſal. 98.</hi> Neceſſe eſt nobis Scripturas ſacras in teſtimonium vocare, ſenſus enim noſtri &amp; enarrationes ſine iis, non habent fidem. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>See</hi> Juſtin. Martyr in Dial. cum Tryphone. Sancta Scriptura ſic fidei noſirae fundamenta proponit, &amp; doctrinae noſtrae regulam figit, ut fides Chriſtianorum iis ſolum revelatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus nitatur, quae in Canonicis libris continentur. <hi>Dar. de</hi> fratcrna Comm. inter Eccleſ. Evang. <hi>p. 76.</hi> Sicut verbum Dei ſcriptum in practicis vitae Chriſtianae unicae eſt rectitudinis norma: ſic idem verbume ſeu ſcriptura ſacra, unica eſt veritatis norma in Theoreticis fidei Chriſtianae. <hi>See Par. in Gal. 5.</hi>
               </note> keep cloſe to this ſacred and unerring Rule and Canon of the Scriptures? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.16. <hi>Eſay</hi> 8.20. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.23. &amp; 30.5.6.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:165014:8"/>2. Whether among many other <hi>pretious truths,</hi> which the Scriptures hold forth unto us, this be not a ſpeciall one, <hi>viz.</hi> That Jeſus Chriſt, our bleſſed Lord and Saviour, (who having purged away our ſinnes, and is ſate down on the right hand of the Majeſty on High, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.30) hath a ſpiritual Kingdom or Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,<note n="d" place="margin">Obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt, quod Chriſtus non dicit, Regnum meum non eſt in hoc mundo, ſed non eſt de hoc mundo. Et infra, non dieit, Regmon meum non eſt HIC, ſed non eſt HINC. <hi>Nam</hi> Regnum (ſc. Chriſti) eſt hic, &amp; in hoc mundo, Coetus credentium, <hi>&amp;c. vide Heming. Aret. &amp; Muſc. in loc.</hi>
               </note> diſtinct from all the Kingdomes of the world? <hi>Iohn</hi> 18.36. <hi>Ieſus anſwered, My kingdome is not of this world.</hi> 'Tis in this world, but not of this world.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether <hi>this Kingdome</hi> of Chriſt here on earth, ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the World, is not uſually diſtingniſhed into<note n="e" place="bottom">Eccleſiae viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis &amp; inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis diſtinctio, fundatur in ſcripturis. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus in c. 2. ad Rom</hi> The Church is viſible or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible. A di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction not of Genus into ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall ſpecies, but of the ſubject into ſeverall adjuncts. For the ſame Church may be and is viſible and inviſible. <hi>Sedg. Script. a perfect Rule for Church Government.</hi> Irvifibilis autem nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur non quod homines ad eam pertinentes non videantur qua homines, ſed quod non cernantur qua electi ſolus euim Deus novit qui ſunt ſui. <hi>Wolleb. Compend. Theolog. vid. Tilen. Syntag. de Eccleſ. Ellis vind. Cathol. p. 4. c. 2.</hi>
               </note> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and Inviſible, Myſticall and Miniſteriall, or Politicall, conſidered as the object of Faith, or of ſight, and ſenſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of all the elect, diſperſed through the whole world, called (by ſome) the Univerſall Church, or of particular Churches collected and gathered together of <hi>viſible Beleevers,</hi> in this or that place, Towne, Citie, Countrey or Kingdome, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1. 1 Theſſ. 2.14.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether the viſible Kingdome of Chriſt, conſiſting of ſuch particular Churches, and Congregations of Beleevers, gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together according to the order of the Goſpel,<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> My Model of the Primitive Congregationall wayes.</note> hath not a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Government, Order, and Ordinances of viſible Worſhip neceſſarily belonging and appertaining thereunto, according to<note n="g" place="margin">Functiones quas enumerat omnes ſunt Eccleſiaſticae, quibus tunc Apoſtolica authoritate ſic diſtinctis, Miniſterium Eccleſiae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabat, &amp; quae nunc etiam in Eccleſiis conſtitutis vigere debent. <hi>Par. in loc. ad Rom. c. 12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7 8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. &amp; 11, 12, &amp; 14. Chapters, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether this Government and externall ordinances of Worſhip, appertaining to this viſible Church ſtate and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165014:8"/>of Chriſt under the new Teſtament, doe not by Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and appointment ſucceed and come in the roome of thoſe Ordinances and Lawes of Worſhip which the Jewes did enjoy under the old Teſtament, according to the propheſie of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Malachi, chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 11. <hi>For from the riſing of the Sun to, &amp;c. my</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">By the Name of <hi>GOD</hi> is meant his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as appears from verſe <hi>6.</hi> and verſe <hi>12.</hi> of the ſame chapter, and ſo it's often uſed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>Vid. Bernard. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaur. Biblic. and Flac. Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lir. cla Som.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Name is great (or ſhall be great) among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iiles, and in every place incenſe ſhall be offered to my Name, and a pure offering for my Name is (or ſhall be great) among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</hi> And whether the words of Chriſt to the Samaritan Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in<note n="k" place="margin">Nam de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogatione &amp; ceſſatione tam Iudaici quam Samaritani, deinde de inductione veri &amp; ſiuceri cultus mulierculam inſtruxit. <hi>Muſc. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>John</hi> 4.22, 23, 24. doe not very much hold forth the truth hereof; as alſo the ſcope of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> in that the Apoſtle makes it a great part of his work to diſſwade the Jewes from their former Legall Ordinances and Services, and to ſtirre them up to embrace the Ordinances of the Goſpel, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how the government of Chriſt in his Church under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is<note n="l" place="bottom">The government of Chriſts Church under the Goſpel, in reſpect of externall Worſhip and Ordinances, is ſaid to be a better Teſtament in a threefold reſpect. <hi>1.</hi> In reſpect of their uſe, becauſe they preſent Chriſt to the ſoule more lively and clearly, more feelingly and ſpiritually, more fully and abundantly. <hi>2.</hi> In reſpect of their end, becauſe they are to end in heaven, at the comming of Chriſt to glory, whereas thoſe of the Law had their period in the grave of Chriſt. <hi>3.</hi> In reſpect of themſelves: for this is a more perfect teſtimony, the rites being fewer, the queſtions and controverſies are not ſo many as did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe concerning the Legall ceremonies. <hi>Sedgw. Script.</hi> A perfect Rule for Church government p. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> a better Teſtament and Covenant then that of the Law. And whether the viſible Churches of Chriſt under the Goſpel, be not every way<note n="m" place="bottom">As the Jewes had circumciſion for them and their ſeed under the Law; ſo now Beleevers in right conſtituted Churches, have Baptiſme for them and their ſeed. As the Iewes had the Paſſover, ſo Beleevert now have the Supper of the Lord. As the Iewes had Officers to lead them; ſo Beleevers now have Paſtors and Teachers, &amp;c. As the Iewes had the miniſtery of the Law read and preached; ſo Beleevers now have the miniſtery of the Goſpel. As the Iewes had a Temple and an Altar; ſo now Beleevers have Ieſus Chriſt and the Saints in fellowſhip, which are living Temples. And as the Iewes had ſacrifices; ſo now Beleevers have the ſpirituall ſacrifices of Prayer and Praiſes, which they offer to God by Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>1 Pet. 2.5.</hi>
               </note> as compleat in point of Ordinances, as the Nationall Church of the Jewes was under the Law, according to <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.10.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether Jeſus Chriſt the <hi>alone</hi> Head and King of this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church-ſtate, and Kingdome, did not<note n="n" place="margin">Nova Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia ſonare debere ca quae Chriſtus credenda &amp; ſervanda praecepit Diſcipulis. Faceſſere igitur debent traditiones humanae, neque miſceri cum Evangelio Chriſti. <hi>Idem in Matth. 28.20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Himſelfe</hi> inſtitute and ordain thoſe <hi>Holy Ordinances</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> for Beleevers to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165014:9"/>make uſe of in all Ages till his comming again, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.<note n="o" place="margin">Non dicit, Ego enim ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Apoſtolus Apoſtolica vobis authoritate ſic tradidi, ſed ego enim accopt à Domino, quod &amp; tradidi vobis. Ad eandem &amp; nobis reſpiciendum eſt hodie, videndum que ne à uorma illius quolibet deelinemus. Non ſunt audiendi qui praetexunt Patres, Concilia, Magiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium ſpiritus, poteſtatem Eccleſiae, Catholicam confuetudinem, &amp;c. omnia haec poſterius ſunt inducta. Nobis regula veritatis eſſe dobet quae veniat à Chriſto, per illius Apoſtolos tranſmiſſa. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>c. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 23, 24, 25, 26. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. And whether theſe Ordinances of worſhip being <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> it be in the<note n="p" place="bottom">What is made a Law, no authority can pull down, but that which ſets it up.</note> power of any publique or privat perſon on earth, to eauſe an alteration or ceſſation of them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles, who (I ſuppoſe <hi>without controverſie</hi>) lived more highly in God, then any now doe or can, did not in their firſt ordaining and gathering of this viſible Church-ſtate and Kingdome, make <hi>uſe of</hi> Goſpel-ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of worſhip<note n="q" place="margin">Our Lord Ieſus himſelfe did not only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and duties of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for his Churches to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, but was in the uſe of them himſelf. He made uſe of Baptiſme, of the Lords Supper, of publiſhing and preaching the Goſpel, of Prayer, of ſinging Hymnes, or Pſalmes, of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate conſerence, of giving thankes before meat, of praying amongst and for the wicked, of ſociety with the Diſciples, and that after his reſurrection in their meeting together at times of worſhip, &amp;c. And thus it was with the Apoſtles alſo, as is evident to ſuch as are but meanly acquainted with the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in the Scriptures.</note> themſelves, and intend that the Saints that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them ſhould do ſo alſo; yea whether they did not by their own uſe, and practiſe of theſe Goſpel-ordinances of Worſhip, leave to the Saints in ſucceeding ages, a pretious<note n="r" place="bottom">There are three ſorts of workes which Chriſt wrought: <hi>1.</hi> Some, <hi>Qua Deus,</hi> i. as he was God, as working of miracles, pardoning of ſinnes, &amp;c. In theſe we cannot imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him. <hi>2.</hi> Some, <hi>Qua mediator Dei &amp; hominum, i</hi> as he was mediator between God and Man, and ſatisfying Gods juſtice for our ſinnes, and reconciling the world to God: And in theſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can we imitate him. <hi>3.</hi> Some, <hi>Qua homo privatus, i.</hi> as he was a private perſon: and theſe are all ſuch duties as God required in his word to be performed. And herein Chriſt hath given us an example to follow and imitate him. <hi>Vide Zanch. in 1 John 2.6.</hi> Apoſtolos Domini habemus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thores, qui nec ipſi quicquam ex ſuo arbitrio, quod inducerent, eligerunt: ſed acceptam à Chriſto diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinam fideliter Nationtbus adſignaverunt. <hi>Tertul. de praeſcript. adverſ. Haereſ. c. 6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>example,</hi> and ground of encouragement to walk in the ſame way of practiſing and uſing joyntly or apart, thoſe ordinances of worſhip, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their conditions and relations private or publique, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.6. 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 11.1. And whether the practiſe of the primitive Saints and Churches, be not alſo a pattern and copie for belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers now to write after. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4,<note n="ſ" place="bottom">Non vult ergo ut quoſvis temerè imitemur: ſed qui ſunt fimiles Apoſtotis. Nequc etiam Apoſtolis ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter, ſed quatenus Chriſtum imitantur. <hi>Zanch. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17, 18, 19. &amp; 4.9.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Whether the things of Chriſts Church and Kingdome, which we call Goſpel-ordinances, and divine Inſtitutions of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165014:9"/>worſhip under the new Teſtament, as the <hi>preaching of the Goſpel, adminiſtration of the Seales, finging of Pſalmes,</hi> or <hi>Hymnes, Prayer, Conference, &amp;c.</hi> bee not in their nature and uſe ſpirituall,<note n="t" place="margin">The Church is called a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Houſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as in <hi>1 Pet. 2.5.</hi> The worſhip called ſpirituall Sacrifices. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>1 Pet. 2.5.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Col. 3.16.</hi> The worſhipers called holy and Spirituall, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Phil. 3.3. 2 Pet. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> So Chriſt, the ſubſtance of the Ordinances, is called ſpirituall meat and drinke, <hi>1 Cor. 12.3.4.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. We may read the nature of many things in their offects. All the Ordinances of worſhip bear this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription. <hi>Holineſſe to the LORD,</hi> and are appointed to work holineſſe in man. <hi>Caryls duty and endeavour of the Saints. p. 28.</hi>
               </note> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. &amp;c. And whether there may not bee abundance of ſweet delight, and ſoule-ſatisfying comfort and content found, if holy and ſpirituall hearts meet with them, and are acted on Chriſt in the uſe of them.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Whether thoſe Divine and Spirituall Offices, Officers, and Ordinances inſtituted by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, are not his<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, rota, Chariots uſing to run on wheeles.</note> 
               <hi>Chariot,</hi> in which he rides gloriouſly in his Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and by which (through his Spirit) he not onely ſubdues his enemies, and conquers the hearts of <hi>Sinners</hi> to himſelfe, (that his father hath given to him from all eternity) but more and more workes over the hearts of the <hi>Saints</hi> themſelves, to a further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of ſubjection to his Scepter, <hi>Cant.</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Ainſworth by this Chariot, underſtands more eſpecially the Church and Miniſters of the Goſpel, holding forth the word of Truth, and Chriſt in the midſt of them ſitting, teaching, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning, and triumphing. <hi>So Merc. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 3.9, 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.2. And I ſaw and behold, a<note n="x" place="bottom">By white Horſe, <hi>Paraens</hi> on the place underſtands the Church <hi>puritate doctrinae &amp; diſciplinae nitidam:</hi> and by him that ſate on it, Chriſt, who is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried or born (as it were) in the Ordinances with great triumph, according to <hi>Acts 9.15.</hi>
               </note> white horſe, and hee that ſate on him had a Bow, and a Crown was given to him, and hee went forth conquering and to conquer.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Whether there be not many <hi>ſingular</hi> &amp; <hi>choyce</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Promiſes of ſalvation to worſhip in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. <hi>Rom. 10.12, 13. 2.</hi> Promiſes in particular, and ſo <hi>1.</hi> to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of prayer, <hi>1.</hi> Of Preparation and aſſiſtance, <hi>Pſa. 10.17. Rom. 8.26. 2.</hi> Of Acceptation, <hi>Eſa. 60.7. Ezek. 43 17. 1 Pet. 2.5. 3.</hi> Of conſolation, <hi>Eſa. 56.7. 4.</hi> Of anſwering and recompenſing, <hi>Pſal. 86.5. &amp; 145.18. &amp; Epheſ. 6.8. Matth. 6.6. Jam. 5.15, 16. Joh. 14.13. &amp; 15.16. &amp; 16.23. 2.</hi> To preaching and hearing of theword, and adminiſtring the Seales, <hi>Matth. 28.20. Prov. 8.34, 35. Eſa. 55.1, 2, 3. 1 Cor. 10.16. Eſa. 25.6. Pſal. 36.8. Cant. 2.3, 4. &amp; 5. 1. Eſa. 12.3. 3.</hi> To conference, <hi>Mal. 3.16; 17. 4</hi> To ſanctifying the Sabbath, or Lords day, <hi>Eſa. 58.13, 14. Eſa. 56.2.5, 6, 7. Jer. 17.24, 25. 5.</hi> To praiſing of God, <hi>Pſal. 50 23. Pſal. 7.5, 6. 6.</hi> To the Aſſemblies and Church-meetings of the Saints to worſhip God: <hi>1.</hi> Of Chriſts preſence with it, <hi>Mat. 18.20. 2.</hi> Protection over it, <hi>Mat. 16.18. Pſal. 84.11. Eſa. 33.20, 21. Eſa. 4.5. 3</hi> Bleſſings of all ſorts upon it, Temporall, ſpirituall, eternall, <hi>Pſa. 84.11. 1, 2.15.128.56.92.13, 14.</hi> and <hi>94.14.65.4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Promiſes</hi> made by Chriſt to beleevers, whiles they abide and continue in the right &amp; pure uſe of thoſe Ordinances and duties of Worſhip, and many ſad and direfull threatnings and comminations to thoſe that neglect, leave and forſake the uſe and practiſe of them, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 97.7. <hi>Ier.</hi> 10.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38, 39. <hi>Luke</hi> 10, 11, 12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:165014:10"/>11. Whether to caſt off the uſe of Goſpel-ordinances, &amp; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend onely to live in God, be not to make Chriſt and his Spirit to <hi>act contrary</hi> to their own <hi>Sacred</hi> Lawes, Inſtitutions, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> given to beleevers in the Scriptures to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: and when or where it was or is to be found in all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that Jeſus Chriſt hath, or doth ſo lead the Saints out of, or take them<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Quaeſt. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> off from the duties of his worſhip, and bid them to ceaſe calling upon the Name of the Lord, ſeeing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures hold forth the contrary. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Pray without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. Whether a beleevers living in God, or in the Spirit, and boſome of the Father, and uſing of Goſpel-ordinances, may not very well ſtand<note n="z" place="margin">The nearer we are to God, the more in love we ſhall be with ſpirituall exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, and with all meanes to draw nigh to him, as Bookes, Sermons, good company, &amp;c. Dr <hi>Sibbs in his Saints Happineſſe,</hi> p. <hi>65.</hi>
               </note> together: And whether the right uſe of thoſe<note n="a" place="margin">Therefore the Lord converghes himſelfe to the poore ſoule by an ordinance; which is ſuch a thing as conſiſts of a ſpiritual and yet an external and ſenſible nature. An Ordinance is the ſubject by which God communicateth himſelfe and his goodneſſe with a power of his Spirit to carry them to the ſoule, as by preaching of the word to the care, through the ſound of a mortall voyce: by prayer, conſiſting outwardly of ſentences and order: by the Sacrament alſo, ſtanding of outward weak Elements. The Lord car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to the ſoule by theſe, moſt inward and ſpirituall things. <hi>Rog. Treat. de Sacram. p. 247.</hi>
               </note> Ordinances which Chriſt hath commanded, will not very much further, and advance a perſons living in the God of thoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, conſidering, that through the preſence of Chriſt with them, and the bleſſing of Chriſt upon them, the heart of a belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is made the more ſpirituall and heavenly.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Whether the Scriptures doe not joyn the greateſt enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, with the greateſt performance of duty towards God, and the greateſt faith with the greateſt obedience, and the greateſt ſenſe of love with the greateſt care of ſervice, as <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:165014:10"/>119.32. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.16, 17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.48.<note n="b" place="margin">The Apoſtles meaning is, that we not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly try, approve, and practiſe thoſe things which poſſibly may be pleaſing to God in ſome low degree, ſuch things as ſet us a ſtep beyond his diſpleaſure; but we muſt ſearch and doe thoſe things which give him higheſt content, and carry us furtheſt into his favour. Things which come up to the exacteſt Rule, and beare trueſt proportion to the ſtandards of Truth and Holineſſe. <hi>Car. preſent duty and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the Saints. p. 9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.47.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Whether to live in God, and neglect the uſe of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, be not a dividing between the end and the meanes, Chriſt having ſanctified Ordinances as pretious<note n="c" place="margin">Experience teacheth, that the fellowſhip of the Word, Prayer, and the like, is the life, ſtrength, blood and marrow of communion. Hence it is that they are called the Banners, Enſignes, Standards of Chriſt, and the Miniſters the hearers thereof. For as Souldiers flock to the Standard and Enſigne, ſo doe the Doves of Chriſt to theſe windowes, &amp;c. <hi>Rog. pract. Chat. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>01.</hi>
               </note> helps and furtherances to the Saints in their fellowſhip with God and one another, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.3, 4. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.32. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. And whether to divide between the end and the meanes, which God hath decreed and Chriſt inſtituted, bee not to make (in this reſpect) the will and minde of God, and Jeſus Chriſt, voyd and of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Whether thoſe that are true beleevers, ſhould in the leaſt refuſe to own and to act in the uſe of thoſe duties and Ordinances of worſhip which the eternall God himſelfe doth not refuſe to own, and to act in and work by to the end of the world,<note n="d" place="margin">The word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, rendred by <hi>Hen. Stepb. Conſummatio.</hi> Matth. 13.39.49.</note> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 0 And whether that place of our Saviour in<note n="*" place="margin">Exhortatio hinc ſumatur ut nos verae Eccleſiae adjungamus ſententia, voluntate, confeſſione, cultut <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; ſejungamus nos ab illis coetibue, qui vel in totam doctrinam. Eccleſiae abjiciunt, u Mahometiſtae; vel fundamentum, hoc eſt doctrinam, articulos fidei, &amp; verum Dei cultum ſubruunt quovis modo ut Papiſtae. <hi>Heming. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 4, 22, 23, 24. doth not hold forth thus much unto us, in that he ſaith to the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> that the Father ſeeketh after ſuch to worſhip him, as worſhip him <hi>in Spirit and in Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. Whether the <hi>cleareſt</hi> demonſtration that can poſſibly be given of a perſons living in God, be not his holy <hi>walking with God,</hi> and living <hi>to</hi> and <hi>for God,</hi> as the Saints have done in <hi>former</hi> ages, and as the Scripture is cleare for, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.8. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.19. And whether to walk with God, and live to God, be not to <hi>deny</hi> our ſelves, and all that is <hi>ours,</hi> (in <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165014:11"/>or practiſe</hi>) and to ſubject our ſelves to the obedience of all that <hi>is his,</hi> that in all things he may be <hi>honoured by us,</hi> according as he is worthy. And whether the ſubjecting of our ſelves to all that the Lord hath made known to be <hi>His,</hi> in his <hi>Word,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing matters of Doctrine and Worſhip, be not the <hi>next</hi> way to honour and exalt his <hi>great Name</hi> before the world, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Whether a perſon, as he is a Beleever, and a Chriſtian, hath not a <hi>generall</hi> calling to walk in, in which he is in a more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate and ſpeciall manner<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.24</note> to <hi>walk</hi> with God, and doe him ſervice in the duties of his worſhip publickly and privatly, as well as a <hi>particular</hi> calling, as they are men, in which they have more <hi>immediate commerſe</hi> with the creature: And whether the <hi>duties</hi> of their generall callings, as they are beleevers, are not of as <hi>great</hi> a conſequence, and as <hi>much</hi> to be lookt after in order to the honour and glory of <hi>God,</hi> and their own <hi>ſpirituall</hi> welfare, as the duties of their particular callings for the good of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> in which they live, and their own <hi>temporall,</hi> welfare; and if that a perſons living ſo highly in God, (as the caſters off of holy duties and Ordinances ſpeak ſo much of) doe not take us <hi>from,</hi> nor <hi>deſtroy</hi> the performance of the duties of our particular callings, as we are men, which are <hi>the leſſe;</hi> how can they, or why ſhould they take <hi>us from</hi> or <hi>deſtroy</hi> the performance of the duties of our generall callings, which are the <hi>greater?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. Whether there be not ſinnes of <hi>omiſſion</hi> as well as ſins of <hi>commiſſion,</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> which Chriſtians may become guilty of: And whether the rejecting and caſting off the duties of Gods Worſhip, either in <hi>publique</hi> or <hi>private,</hi> or <hi>both,</hi> be not a ſinne of this <hi>Nature in a high degree:</hi> And whether ſuch a ſinne of <hi>omiſſion reigning</hi> in a perſon that <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends</hi> to godlineſſe, doth not declare him to be<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>The wicked in Scripture are characteriz'd by ſuch kindes of ſinnes as the ſinne of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> Jerem. 10.25. Pſalm 10.4. Hoſea 4.1. Eccles. 9.2. Malach. 3.18. Matth. 25.41, 42, 43. Vide Reig. vol. 2. p. 297. Vid. Quaeſt. 26.</note> 
               <hi>out</hi> of Chriſt, and the ſtate of grace, ſeeing that no reigning ſinne can <hi>poſſibly ſtand</hi> with a perſons being in Chriſt, according to <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6, 7, 11, 12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Whether there be not a marvellous ſlighting and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165014:11"/>of the<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 2, 3.</hi> Wiſdome bath built her Houſe: <hi>i.</hi> Chriſt who is the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in whom are hid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>i.</hi> All the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Coloſſ. 2.3.</hi>
               </note> wiſdome and faithfulneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt, to caſt his holy<note n="g" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Heb. 3.2, 5, 6.</hi> If Moſes the ſervant was no couſeuing Merchant, but faithfull to him that intruſted him, in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing the ordinances of legall ſervice, how much more faithfull was Chriſt the Sonne in appointing the ordinances of Evangelicall ſervice?</note> Ordinances of divine worſhip, which he himſelfe hath inſtituted, and given a Being unto in his kingdome <hi>behind our backes:</hi> And whether it be little leſſe then blaſphemy to ſpeake diſgracefully of the ſacred things of his Houſe,<note n="h" place="bottom">The word ſignifieth to ſpeake diſgracefully, or to take away the fame, credit, or good name of another, from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>famam alterius laedere. Vide</hi> the workes of <hi>Mr. Sedgwick, Mr. Saltmarſh, Mr. Wilk, Mr. Avery,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and the Scriptures in which they are recorded, calling them <hi>poore, low diſpenſations, childiſh things, gold and ſilver Idols, empty formes,</hi> and ſuch like ignominious ſpeech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, if not a great deale worſe (though the leaſt of them doth not become any, much leſſe thoſe that <hi>pretend to live in God,</hi> to utter and make uſe of.) And yet further, whether ſuch <hi>practiſes</hi> of caſting off, and <hi>reviling</hi> the Ordinances and Churches of Chriſt (if <hi>willingly and knowingly</hi> done) be not a <hi>high ſtep</hi> to that<note n="i" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendat igitur nobis, &amp;c.</hi> He therefore commendeth to us love and reverence to the Miniſtery of the Church, and the ſtudy of frequenting Church-Aſſemblies, from the danger of thoſe who neglecting them, doe wander away and tempt God. <hi>Paraeus in loc. And then ſheweth what the particular ſteps to the unpardonable ſinne are: 1.</hi> A defection from the Aſſemblies of the Saints, or Church-communion. <hi>2.</hi> A voluntary abnegation of the truth formerly acknowledged. <hi>3.</hi> A malicious oppoſing and perſecuting it. <hi>4.</hi> A defection joyned with ſcorning and deriding. <hi>5.</hi> A finall perſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and perſevering in ſuch a defection, &amp;c. <hi>id. ibid.</hi>
               </note> unpardonable ſinne againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> according to <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25, 26.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Whether ſuch perſons as caſt off, and contend againſt the uſe of divine Ordinances, doe not <hi>ex diametro, i.</hi> directly croſſe, and goe againſt (not <hi>onely others</hi>) but their <hi>own former experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> (if ever they had any) of thoſe <hi>inexpreſſable Incomes</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and diſcoveries of <hi>Divine love,</hi> and favour, which they have enjoyed both in <hi>publique</hi> ordinances, and <hi>private</hi> duties of worſhip, which <hi>time was,</hi> they would not have given, nor parted with for all the treaſure and pleaſure of the whole world, though now they judge lightly of them, and look upon as deluſions of their own hearts, or things of no account, or value.</p>
            <p n="21">21. Whether <hi>caſting off</hi> of <hi>Divine</hi> Ordinances, and <hi>forſaking</hi> the Aſſemblies of the Saints, that have fellowſhip together in the worſhip of God, be not ſo farre from living in God, as 'tis ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Scripture ſence, a living<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cron. 15.3. Eph. 2.12.</note> without God, yea a depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from him, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165014:12"/>which place is to be underſtood of Goſpel-worſhip, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by comparing it with the 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 verſes of the ſame chapter, where the Apoſtle makes compariſon between Chriſt and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſhewes how farre the Lord Jeſus Chriſt excells <hi>Moſes</hi> in building and ordering the Houſe of God with all the Ordinances of worſhip belonging thereunto under the Goſpel, And thus <hi>Cain</hi> is ſaid to goe out from the preſence of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.16. or from <hi>Gods</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> à facie Domini.</note> 
               <hi>face.</hi> Now what is ſignified by this, but his being removed from the wayes and meanes of enjoying the favour of God, which are his<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>So the face of God is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently taken in Scripture, Pſal. 24.6. Pſal. 27.8. Pſal. 105.4. Jonah 1.3.</hi> Quare non dubito ſub hac voce notari adminicula quibus Deus nos ad ſe tollit, ex ſua immenſa gloria ad nos deſcendens, atque in terra nobis proponens imaginem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eleſtis ſuae gloriae caeterum quia in unius Dei arbitrio eſt ſe nobis conſpiciendum praebere (quod facit in verbo &amp; ſacramentis) in hoc intuitu oculos retineri decet ne nobis contingat quod Papiſtis, <hi>&amp;c. Calv. in Pſal. 27.8. Vide Sal. Glaſſ. Philalog. ſac. in verb. p. 104.</hi>
               </note> Ordinances, and therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his <hi>Face,</hi> becauſe in theſe he uſeth to manifeſt himſelfe to his people, as two friends are ſaid to doe when they ſpeak <hi>face to face</hi> to each other.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Whether the promiſes of the Goſpel <hi>(excepting onely that great and abſolute</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 2; 8. Ioh. 6.37.39. Iſai. 49.8.9</note> 
               <hi>firſt promiſe of calling the elect to Chriſt)</hi> do not carry and contain in the bowels of them the matter of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,</hi> and thoſe rewards ſtand in<note n="*" place="margin">The promiſes are free in <hi>fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> being made onely out of grace, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall in <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto eſſe,</hi> being performed and accompliſhed with dependance on duties in us, <hi>Reign. Synf. of Sin. p. 337. &amp; 364. Vide Stock on Mal. cap. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Relation</hi> to preſuppoſed ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and duties to be performed by beleevers in order to their enjoying thoſe Rewards, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.7, 8. <hi>Ask and it ſhall be given to you.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ</hi> 3.4, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.9 <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.14. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.8. &amp; 10, 11 And whether a perſon can expect the performance of the Reward on <hi>Gods part,</hi> that neglects the duty required on his <hi>own part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. Whether one main end of the new Covenant of grace, mentioned <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.33. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.9, 10. wherein God promiſeth to give his Spirit, be not to <hi>enable Beleevers,</hi> and cauſe them to walk in all the Statutes and Ordinances of the Lord Jeſus, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> The roat <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is very empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, and fignifies, <hi>ad certum uſum aptare vel diſponere: i.</hi> To diſpoſe &amp; fit a perſon for employment, taken from dreſſing and making ready of meats and ſacrifices under the Law. <hi>Vide Sheind. Lexic. penta Hutt. Heb. Bib. cum Cub. Leigh erit ſac. Heb. in Radie.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. And whether a departing from Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and ceaſing to walk in a right obſervation of them, be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165014:12"/>not a terrible <hi>ſhaking,</hi> if not a making of this glorious new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace (in this reſpect) <hi>void</hi> to the Saints: For to what purpoſe is there a Covenant made with the elect in Chriſt, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able them to walk with God in all the righteous Statutes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God, if there be none to be obſerved by them?</p>
            <p n="24">24. Whether a perſons ceaſing to perform the duty of prayer, and other duties of Gods worſhip, and to live onely in God <hi>(as ſuch ſay that are againſt Ordinances)</hi> be not deſtructive to the Mediatorſhip of Jeſus Chriſt, and all his glorious offices belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto, eſpecially that of his <hi>Prieſtly</hi> office, whereby hee makes continuall <hi>Interceſſion</hi> for true Beleevers, and by which we are made acceptable to God, <hi>Rom</hi> 8.34 <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.6. And whether (in this reſpect) it be not to raze the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all our faith and hope in God for juſtification and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation alone by Chriſt; yea, a razing of the very foundation of all true Chriſtian Religion, and according to the Apoſtle, to <hi>preach another Goſpel, Gal.</hi> 1 8 9. For if there be no more need of the performance of the duties of Gods worſhip, in which <hi>(through Chriſt)</hi> we draw nigh to God (but the ſoule is to bee caught and ſwallowed up wholly into God, as theſe men ſpeake that deny the uſe of Ordinances) then to what purpoſe is Chriſts Prieſtly office now on foot, to make our perſons and Goſpel ſpirituall ſacrifices and ſervices of prayer and praiſes acceptable to the Father, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</p>
            <p n="25">25 Whether to leave off, and altogether to ceaſe the uſe of Goſpel-ordinances and duties of Gods worſhip, be not directly againſt the <hi>revealed will</hi> and minde of God, and Jeſus Chriſt contained in the Scriptures, that<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 29.18. Ier. 29.12, 13 Zech. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.17. Ioh. 10.16. Epheſ. 6.18. 2 Tim. 2.22. 1 Cor. 11.26. Heb. 3.7, 11. Heb. 10.25. Jam. 1.18, 19, ad finem.</note> expreſly command &amp; require the continuall performance of theſe duties, as <hi>hearing the Word, Prayer, adminiſtration of the Seales, Church-communion,</hi> &amp;c. And whether this practice doth not proceed from a <hi>Popiſh, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Spirit, to make, and bring perſons (in a <hi>great meaſure</hi>) to forſake the holy Scriptures (which ought to be the<note n="*" place="margin">All Writers both ancient &amp; modern, that are ſound and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, averre ſo much, as may be ſeen abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly in their works againſt the Papiſts and Hereticks, in all ages from the Apoſtles to to this day.</note> only and ſole Rule in all matters of faith) &amp; prefer mens private thoughts, opinions, inventions, and <hi>unwritten Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> above them, as is the practice of idolatrous and Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Papiſts to doe; yea whether ſuch a principle as this, to caſt off the duties of Gods worſhip, ſo expreſly commanded in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be performed, be not with the Papiſts, (the great ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165014:13"/>of Chriſt and his Goſpel-inſtitutions, to call for an <hi>Index Expurgatorius,</hi> to correct and cancell thoſe many pretious Texts and places in the Scripture, that are <hi>point blank</hi> againſt this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous opinion of forſaking Church-Aſſemblies, and uſe of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, as they doe many places of <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtles, that hold forth juſtification <hi>E ſola fide,</hi> i. by Faith alone without works.</p>
            <p n="26">26. Whether the Scriptures doe not number and reckon ſuch perſons as caſt off Ordinances amongſt the vileſt of men, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane<note n="a" place="margin">The children of God by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing are better known, then by calling upon him. <hi>Barlow on 2 Tim. 2.2.</hi> Let them goe branded like Satans ſlaves, ſounes of Belial, who omit this duty. <hi>Id. ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> that make not conſcience of the obſerving of them, but caſt his Lawes behinde their backes, and count them grievous, and doe what in them lies to make them void, as <hi>Nehem</hi> 9.26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.126. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 53.4. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.13, 14. and in eſpeciall that of prayer, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Job</hi> 27.10.<note n="b" place="margin">Eſt emm hoc mortalium ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis inſitum, ut Deo offerendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. <hi>Muſc. in Joh.</hi>
               </note> the law of <hi>Nature</hi> teaching men to worſhip and ſerve that God whom they acknowledge, (as we ſee in the practice of the meere Heathens, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. and 2. <hi>chap.</hi>) and the law of <hi>Grace</hi> teaching men to delight in that God and his worſhip, whom they ſo draw nigh unto by faith in Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.97.103. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.3. <hi>Acts</hi> 2 46, 47. And whether that place in<note n="c" place="margin">This is evident from the Apoſtles quoting this Text in <hi>Acts 4.25, 26, 27.</hi> againſt the Rulers, Elders, Scribes, &amp;c that ſate in counſell againſt them, and made open oppoſition againſt Chriſt in them, refuſing to bow to his Scepter and Government held forth both in the Doctrine and practice of the Apoſtles. And to this agree Expoſitors generally.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. be not meant of thoſe wicked men (more eſpecially) that caſt off all Divine Ordinances and Lawes of Chriſts Kingdome and Government under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Whether the <hi>Face</hi> of Chriſt, in which the <hi>Glory</hi> of God the Father doth ſhine forth<note n="d" place="margin">Non loquitur autem de corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea Chriſti fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; ſed de ea quae ſalutis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ſpectan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam proponit. <hi>Muſc. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. be not to be underſtood of Goſpel-ordinances and Inſtitutions, Chriſt himſelfe perſonally being now ſate down at the right hand of the Majeſty on high, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. In which <hi>Face,</hi> or <hi>Miniſtery</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Chriſt, the admirable and illuſtrious beauty of the <hi>eternall God,</hi> his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite wiſdome, power and love, (which is hid from the world) doth ſo ſhine forth oftentimes, through the Spirit of Chriſt to the hearts of the Saints, that they ſeem to be out of the body, and in heaven, before they are in heaven, and in glory on this ſide glory, as it was with <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.1, 2. And whether a Beleever be not bound to be in the uſe of theſe Goſpel-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165014:13"/>and adminiſtrations, where he may<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 27.4.</note> behold this beauty and glory of the Lord, it being the Lords own way he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to reveale himſelfe by, and not truſt to other wayes of our own making, for the ſight of this glory, having not a warrant for it in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="28">28. Whether a Beleever in this life, whiles he is cloathed with his <hi>earthly</hi> Tabernacle, can ſee <hi>Spirituall</hi> things, eſpecially <hi>God Himſelfe,</hi> who is an infinite and incomprehenſible <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſo as to have fellowſhip and communion with him, and to live in him, otherwiſe then by an eye of faith, in the<note n="e" place="margin">We cannot ſee Divine things othewiſe then in a glaſſe: that ſight of God which wee ſhall have immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in heaven without the Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, is of a higher na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, when we ſhall be perfect; but while we live here, we cannot ſee God but in Chriſt; and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee Chriſt but in the Word and Sacraments, ſuch is the imperfection of our fight. <hi>Dr. Sibs Excel. of the Goſpel above the Law, p. 280, 281, 286, 287,</hi> &amp;c.</note> glaſſe of Goſpel-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, as the <hi>works</hi> of God, and the <hi>word</hi> of God; but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who is God incarnate, God manifeſt in the fleſh, and this Jeſus in the myſtery of the Goſpel, and Seales, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> And whether the Lord doth not, (as a great teſtimony of his love to us in Chriſt) very much condeſcend and ſtoop to the weake and imperfect condition of his people, while they are here below, to make known the glory of his <hi>Wiſdome, Mercy, Power,</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> to their ſoules by his Spirit in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</p>
            <p n="29">29. Whether the Commandements of Chriſt, ſo much ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of and mentioned in the Scriptures, doe not extend to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the <hi>outward man,</hi> as well as the <hi>inward,</hi> and to the <hi>externals</hi> of worſhip as well as the <hi>internals</hi> of faith: And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a perſon can upon <hi>Iuſt grounds,</hi> number himſelfe among the friends of Chriſt, that doth not make conſcience of<note n="f" place="margin">Nota igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur verae ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citiae eſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervantia vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatis amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voluntas Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti eſt in illius praeceptis; illis obedtre eſt vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntati Chriſti eſte conformem. Amici Chriſti non ſunt, qui Chriſti praecepta ſuſque de<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> facientes doctrinis &amp; mandatis hominum ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jiciuntur, <hi>Muſc. in loc.</hi>
               </note> keeping thoſe commandements of Chriſt, according to that of our Saviour, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.14. Yea, whether any one can ſay upon juſt grounds that he loves or knowes Chriſt, that doth not keep his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, ſeeing the Scriptures ſpeak directly againſt it, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſuch for lyers that pretend to know Chriſt, and love him, but yet keep not his commandements,<note n="g" place="margin">Neceſſario igitur conſequi quicunque jactant ſidem ſen ſtudium pietatis, et interim ſtudium ſervandae legis Dei negligunt, eos impudentiſſimc mentiri, <hi>Zanch in loc.</hi>
               </note> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3, 4. <hi>Iohn</hi> 14, 15.</p>
            <p n="30">30. Whether the end of Chriſts comming into the world,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165014:14"/>were not rather to fulfill and <hi>confirme,</hi> then to <hi>diſanull</hi> and make void the law of God ingraven in our hearts, and revealed in the Scriptures, whereby he calls for the obedience of the <hi>whole man,</hi> inward and outward, in the ſervice of Chriſt. And whether ſuch as break the <hi>leaſt</hi> of theſe lawes, and ſhall <hi>teach others</hi> to doe ſo likewiſe, doe not bring themſelves under that penalty of <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.15. to be counted<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>i. e,</hi> minimi fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, imò nihili fiet, vult e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim dicere, illos excluſum iri è regno coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum. <hi>Piſcat. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>leaſt</hi> in the Kingdome of heaven, that is, to have no part nor portion in the Church of Chriſt here on earth, or the Kingdome of glory hereafter.</p>
            <p n="31">31. Whether thoſe that enter on the actions and workes of their particular callings, or upon the uſe of the creature, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the accuſtomed times of refreſhing <hi>Nature,</hi> as at <hi>Dinner, Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, &amp;c.</hi> without ſeeking to God by prayer for, &amp; praiſes through faith in Chriſt, can <hi>expect a bleſſing</hi> upon them, or a <hi>ſanctified</hi> and comfortable uſe of them. And whether they doe not <hi>tranſgreſſe</hi> the revealed will of God expreſly maniſeſted herein, and diſcover a <hi>looſe,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Let us never come to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble without cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon Gods name, let us ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver riſe from the table without giving tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks; for it is certain, that all they that eat ſo, and doe not pray to God, are for the moſt part worſe then bruit beaſts. <hi>Calv Serm. in 1 Tim. 4.3, 4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>brutiſh,</hi> and <hi>prophane</hi> frame of Spirit herein, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Be carefull for nothing, but in every thing by prayer and ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with thankeſgiving, let your requeſts bee made knowne to God.</hi> So 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Pray without ceaſing,</hi> and the 18. <hi>verſe, In every thing give thankes, for this is the will of God in Chriſt Jeſus concerning you</hi> So 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4.5 ſpeaking of meats that ſeducing Teachers ſhould in the latter times endeavour in a<note n="k" place="margin">As on Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, in Lent, in Embring dayes, and faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dayes, <hi>&amp;c. Calv. Id ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> manner to cauſe people to abſtain from, he ſaith, that God hath <hi>created them to be received with</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Sic paſſim Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus cibum ſumpturus ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum aſpiciens et coelum in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vens, benedicit patri, et gratias agit. <hi>Mat. 14.15, 26. Marc. 6..</hi> Sic Paulus <hi>Acts 27. 1 Cor. 10.31,</hi> ad hunc inquam uſum cibos Deus fecit, <hi>Claud. Eſpenc. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>thankeſgiving;</hi> ſo that a chiefe <hi>end</hi> of Gods creating every creature for mans uſe is, that they ſhould be uſed with <hi>thankeſgiving,</hi> and that they are not ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified and bleſſed to us, without the <hi>Word and Prayer:</hi> i.e. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out acting<note n="m" place="margin">The Sun is a noble creature of it ſelf, and yet the brightnes of it cannot come to us but to our condemnation, unleſſe it be ſanctified to us. By what, means? By faith. So fareth it with meat and drink, and all the reſt. <hi>Calv. ut ſupra.</hi>
               </note> faith and Chriſt a <hi>promiſe,</hi> and deſiring God wee may ſo receive it, and have it bleſſed to us; ſo that to <hi>neglect pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and the <hi>exerciſe of faith</hi> in the <hi>promiſe,</hi> and giving thankes for all <hi>by Chriſt,</hi> we doe not onely fruſtrate and make void the end for which at firſt the Lord created them for our uſe, but we are deprived of that comfort that doth attend them, to thoſe that are in Chriſt, and are at no better paſſe under the enjoyments of them, then thoſe are that are out of Chriſt, who are wicked, prophane, and brutiſh, like the ſwine that feeds on the <hi>Acornes,</hi> that are under the tree, but never looks up from whence they fall.</p>
            <p n="32">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:165014:14"/>32. Whether the Scriptures do not hold forth unto us, that the greateſt and higheſt enjoyments of God in the Spirit, which the Saints have attained unto in this life, have been in their <hi>diligent uſe</hi> and <hi>improvement</hi> of Divine Goſpel-ordinances, and duties of worſhip, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.21, &amp; 9.11, 12. &amp; 10.9.44. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.6, 7, 8, 9 And whether the Scriptures ſhew unto us any other way, wherein the Lord of glory hath ordinarily appeared unto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, beſides that of his ordinances, to the helping of them upon all occaſions, as their neceſſities have required.</p>
            <p n="33">33. Whether departing from Goſpel-ordinances, and Societies of the Saints in the pure worſhip of God, bee not a <hi>notable trick</hi> (if not a ſtrong <hi>deluſion</hi>) of the <hi>Devill,</hi> which he makes uſe of, the better to further his curſed deſigne, upon the Lords people, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them off from their<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>firſt love,</hi> and cooling (if not quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) that ſacred heat, and fervour of the Spirit, that they formerly manifeſted in the ſervice and worſhip of God, preſcribed by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: And whether ſad and lamentable experience doth not evidence ſo much, in ſome that are now changed in their walking, from what they were <hi>formerly,</hi> being as barren and empty in ſpiritual actions and aſſections as thoſe that never knew what it was to be exerciſed in them, and as much to ſeek of their <hi>tenderneſſe,</hi> that once they manifeſted in reſpect of ſinne,<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Contrary to Mat. 5.4. Mat. 26.75. 1 Cor. 5.2. with 2 Cor. 7.7, 9, 11. 1 Cor. 11.30, 31. Iam. 4.9, 10. 1 Ioh. 1.9. Zech. 12.10.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, fig: luxum et delitias. Inde verbum <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, delicate vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, deliciari, voluptatibus indulgere. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. In deceptionibus ſuis. Cum meudaciis et impoſturis ſuis deceperint fimplives Chriſtianos et pecunia eoſdem e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>erint, poſtea ean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem in ſplendida et lauta convivia in aleam ſtructuras magniſicas et ſcorta profundunt. <hi>Oſiand. vide Gerrard. in loc.</hi>
               </note> as that they judge it no other then a <hi>Spirit of bondage</hi> to been humbled for it, making no ſcruple at all to have fellowſhip with the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull workes</hi> (and workers) <hi>of darkneſſe,</hi> which the Saints are commanded to reprove and flye from, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.11. yea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found in the number of thoſe that<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>ſport</hi> themſelves with their own <hi>deceivings,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 13.</p>
            <p n="34">34. Whether it be not a principall part of that great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>Heart-deceitfulneſſe</hi> is within us, to conceive, that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in God will dead a Chriſtian to the uſe and practiſe of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and performance of holy duties, when the chiefe end of a perſons living in God is to dead the heart to ſinne, and take it off from carnall and wordly things, that obſtruct and hinder his communion with God, and to quicken it to Ordinances, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165014:15"/>ſpirituall duties; by the uſe of which (through the <hi>mighty work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit of Chriſt</hi>) his communion with, &amp; communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from God, are increaſed, and perfected day by day. And whether (to ſpeak properly) the more a perſon lives in the Spirit, the more that perſon be not<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 5.16. Vide Par. in loc.</note> lifted off from <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Selfe,</hi> and worldld carnall delights, to walk cloſely with God in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his generall and particular callings; the contrary to which we too much finde and now meet with in thoſe that caſt off Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</p>
            <p n="35">35. Whether Jeſus Chriſt be not infinitely delighted in, and affected with the aſſemblings of the Saints and exerciſings of their gifts and graces in the duties of his worſhip, as appeares every where in the<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant. 2.14. The Hebrew root</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſies prayers, praiſes, ſongs, thankeſgivings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as <hi>Pſal. 5.3.26.7.28.2. vide Ainſworth in loc.</hi> Placet Domino vox Eccleſiae in diſcrimine ad cum conſugient<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſicut de Iſraelitis ad marc interceptis dicitur. <hi>Exod. 14.15.</hi> Vox Eccleſiae eum confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentis et celebrantis, et ejus totus aſpectus, ſpecies, forma ac facies Eccleſiae. <hi>Merc. in loc.</hi>
               </note> Scriptures, by his drawing nigh to them at ſuch times, as to the Eunuch when he was reading the Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.26. to the two Diſciples when they were in conference going to <hi>Emmaus,</hi> to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his friends when they were hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Peter,</hi> to <hi>Paul</hi> when he was in prayer, and <hi>Peter</hi> alſo in the ſame duty, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. &amp; <hi>Acts</hi> 10.</p>
            <p n="36">36. Whether it be not the greateſt unkindneſſe that can be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to the Lord Jeſus, to caſt away, and ſpeak evill of, yea to contend againſt thoſe wayes and meanes in which hee hath moſt of all appeared to them, and ſpoken peace to their ſoules: And whether it be not a grieving of the ſpirit to<note n="q" place="margin">The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> properly ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies baſely to account of a thing, and eſteem it nothing worth. This reproves thoſe who pretend the Spirit, and deſpiſe propheſy, they have the Spirit to guide them, and therefore need no preaching. <hi>Tayl. in his Saints progreſſe to full Holineſſe. p. 46. And then a little after,</hi> Many who have <hi>Jacobs</hi> voyce (ſaith he) profeſſe in word better things, yet prize the preaching of Chriſt as a thing of nought: they think it better to be caſting up ſome account, or reading ſome Hiſtory, or walking in the fields, or viſiting ſome friends, or perhaps going to a Play, then to a Sermon. Are theſe the ſonnes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> or the ſonnes of God, and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſounes of prophane <hi>Eſau? Id. ibid.</hi>
               </note> deſpiſe propheſying, ceaſe praying, and to forſake the Aſſemblies of the Saints, that meet together to worſhip the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Lord of Hoſts,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5, 17, 18, 19, 20.</p>
            <p n="37">37. Whether the Father hath not commanded us to honour the Sonne as we are to honour <hi>himſelfe,</hi> as in <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.22, 23. And whether a perſon may be ſaid truly to honour the <hi>Father,</hi> that<note n="r" place="margin">Quia ut una eſt eſſentia, ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia, potentia, voluntas utriuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, ita etiam honor idem eſt utriuſque, adeo ut qui alterum non honorat, aut ignominia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fficit, is &amp; alterum non bonoret, aut igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miuia afficiat: cum propter identitatem eſſentiae, omnia ipſis ſint communia, adeo ut qui video filium videat patrem, <hi>Ioh. 14.9.</hi> qui confitetur aut negat filium, conſiteatur aut neget &amp; non habe at patrem. <hi>1 Ioh. 2.23. Tarnov. in loc.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:165014:15"/>neglects the honour of Chriſt the Sonne: And whether the caſting off thoſe duties and ordinances of <hi>Worſhip</hi> Chriſt hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted and ordained, yea commanded to be made uſe of, as King of his Church, be not rather a diſhonouring then an honouring of him.</p>
            <p n="38">38. Whether there be any ſuch way for Beleevers ordinarily to promote the honour and glory of Jeſus Chriſt, and proclaime and beare out his Name before the world, then this their holy and conſcientious obſerving the duties of his <hi>Worſhip</hi> at all times, and on all occaſions, eſpecially in times of perſecution: And whether Jeſus Chriſt hath not taken it well at the hands of his Churches, when they have done ſo, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9, 10, 13.</p>
            <p n="39">39. Whether the Saints in the moſt pureſt Goſpel times, that are yet to come, when the <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhal be brought in, and the <hi>Iewes called,</hi> ſhall not then make uſe of <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and duties of <hi>Worſhip,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">In moſt or all theſe places of Scripture is mention made of viſible wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, officers and ordinances, and they are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the moſt godlieſt Interpreters of the purity of thoſe Goſpel dayes and times which ſhall ſucceed the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of Antichriſt, and the calling of the Iewes, as could eaſily be ſhewed, and doubtleſſe ſome of thoſe Texts, if not all of them, are yet to be fulfilled. So that the pureſt Goſpel times ſhall not null, or make void the uſe of Divine Ordinances.</note> 
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.21. to the end of the chap. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17. <hi>Eſay</hi> 2.2, 3, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66, 18. to the end of the Chap. <hi>Mich.</hi> 41, 2. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.9, 10. to the end, <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.11, 22. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.4. with many more. And whether the overthrow of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery and removing of all falſe <hi>Worſhip</hi> at this day in the world, ſhall not be in order to the <hi>introducing</hi> and erecting or ſetting up the true worſhip of Chriſt in this Kingdome among the Saints.</p>
            <p n="40">40. Whether at this preſent juncture of time, when God is appearing in his glory, and ſetting up his King (the Lord Jeſus Chriſt) upon his holy Hill of <hi>Syon,</hi> as he hath promiſed and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of old to doe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.6. there be any thing more <hi>obſtructive,</hi> if not <hi>deſtructive</hi> to the carrying on of this bleſſed work, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as men may judge to outward appearance, then for thoſe that preſend to ſo much of God in them, openly to conteſt againſt the uſe of Divine Ordinances and Inſtitutions of worſhip, wherein a principall part of Chriſts Kingdome on earth confiſteth: And whether many of thoſe that thus reject and deſpiſe the holy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165014:16"/>and Commands of Jeſus Chriſt laid forth in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for all beleevers to obſerve in the worſhipping of God, (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have known and profeſt the ſame) be not like to prove the fitteſt inſtruments in the hands of Satan and Antichriſt (if the Lord of glory prevent not) to <hi>trouble</hi> the peace of the Churches of Chriſt afreſh, after the raging waves of the late tribulations be a little more aſſwaged.</p>
            <p n="41">41. Whether the Scriptures, when they ſpeake of the Saints <hi>drawing nigh to God,</hi> be not meant <hi>of performing the duties of his worſhip,</hi> and drawing nigh to him in Ordinances, as in that of<note n="t" place="margin">Every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance brings us neare to God, <hi>Levit. 10.</hi> The originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in propinquis mels.</hi> The Prieſts under the ceremoniall worſhip had the ſpeciall honour of that Title, to be called <hi>Gods nigh ones, Numb. 16.9.</hi> he cauſed them to come neere him in holy ſervices. Now all the Saints are a holy Prieſthood, to offer up ſpirituall ſacrifices, <hi>1 Pet. 2.5. Caryl Serm. in Iames 4.</hi> See abundance more to this purpoſe in that pretious Sermon. If any deſire further and fuller ſatisfaction in this particular, let him diligently peruſe that excellent Treatiſe of that late emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and pretious ſervant of Chriſt <hi>Mr. Jer. Bur.</hi> called, <hi>Goſpel-worſhip.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. <hi>ult. Iames</hi> 4.8.</p>
            <p n="42">42. Whether thoſe that now caſt off Ordinances, and contend againſt the uſe of them, doe not goe againſt the judgement, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and profeſſion of all the true Churches of Chriſt, that ever were, or are, from the beginning of the world to this day, and not only ſince but before the defection of <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> And whether thoſe that did firſt lead the dance in this unhappy courſe of deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the uſe of Ordinances, were not tainted and corrupted with the fouleſt <hi>Errors,</hi> and greateſt <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> from the <hi>Truth,</hi> that may be, denying the authority of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> denying the <hi>Trinity,</hi> denying the <hi>Divinity of Chriſt,</hi> &amp; of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> denying the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> the <hi>Being of Sin,</hi> or elſe making God the author of it, &amp;c. in whoſe dreadfull ſteps many of late begin to tread, that caſt off the uſe of Gods worſhip and ordinances, as lamentable experience witneſſeth</p>
            <p n="43">43. Whether ſuch as wilfully caſt away the uſe of <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and duties of worſhip, and contend againſt them, have not juſt cauſe to queſtion the truth of their <hi>Spirituall eſtates,</hi> and to doubt whether ever Jeſus Chriſt were rightly <hi>formed</hi> in their hearts, ſeeing the truth of the work depends ordinarily upon the ſame means to build and perfect it, that firſt of all inſtrumentally begat it, which is the publique ordinance of the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as 1. of <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. compared with <hi>Iames</hi> 1.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.21. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18.</p>
            <p n="44">44. Whether departing from the ordinances of God, be not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165014:16"/>one of thoſe<note n="u" place="margin">Theſe are times wherein a ſpirit of error is gone out into the world. That propheſie of Chriſt ſeems (in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in our dayes. <hi>Matth. 24, &amp;c. Vide Car.</hi> Preſent Duty and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour of the Saints. <hi>p, 36, 37.</hi>
               </note> deceivable wayes that <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> and <hi>falſe Chriſts</hi> ſhall make uſe of in theſe <hi>latter dayes</hi> of the world, that are come upon us, to deceive if it were poſſible, the very elect, as Chriſt himſelfe hath forewarned and fore-told, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.24. And whether an elect perſon may not poſſibly be carried away with the <hi>error</hi> of the wicked (againſt which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts, 2 <hi>Pet,</hi> 3.17) <hi>for ſome time, Eſay</hi> 29.24. And whether ſuch may not come to ſee their error this way of <hi>leaving Ordinances,</hi> and <hi>caſting off duties,</hi> before they are out of this world, eſpecially on their <hi>Death-beds,</hi> when they may bewaile it with teares of <hi>blood,</hi> if it were poſſible, ſo ſad may their condition be, as I heard a gracious woman in <hi>London</hi> once to ſpeake of one of her Sex, whom ſhe knew well, that was brought into ſuch a dreadfull condition when ſhe was on her <hi>Death-bed,</hi> for her wilfull ſlighting and caſting off <hi>Ordinances</hi> and <hi>Duties</hi> of Gods worſhip, and pretending onely to Chriſts doing of all for her, and ſhe to do nothing but look to him,<note n="x" place="bottom">Foelix quem faciunt aliena pericula cautum.</note> that ſhe was brought to the very gates of hell and deſperation.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Thoſe happy are that others harmes</l>
               <l>Againſt like evils ſtrongly armes.</l>
            </q>
            <p n="45">45. Whether Apoſtaſie and falling away of Profeſſors from the holy wayes of Gods worſhip, which once they profeſt and practiſed, be not a grievous judgement in it ſelfe, that God juſtly inflicts upon perſons for their unthankfulneſſe, and for unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe under Goſpel-diſpenſations and Adminiſtration, receiving not the truth in the love of it, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.11, 12. And whether this evill be not a cauſe of many other evils to the Kingdome, provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Lord to lengthen out the miſeries of this Nation.</p>
            <p n="46">46. Whether <hi>Anarchy,</hi> or the rejecting of all <hi>Civill</hi> govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a State, be not <hi>eminently</hi> deſtructive to that State and Common-wealth where it once prevails: And whether rejecting of Chriſts ſpirituall Government, Ordinances, and Lawes of <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> be not to introduce a ſpirituall <hi>Anarchy</hi> into his Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and Kingdome, which he hath in the world, and is daily more and more advancing, and conſequently an endeavouring (according to what lies in the power of creatures) to ſubvert and overthrow the glorious Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt, and to lay his honour in the duſt: And whether thoſe that ſhall perſiſt and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165014:17"/>perſevere in <hi>ſuch ondeavours,</hi> deſerve not to be <hi>branded</hi> for ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the glory and dignity of him whom the Eternall <hi>God</hi> hath exalted to be the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> and to whom whoſoever ſhall refuſe to yeeld ſubjection (be he <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Peaſant</hi>) ſhall be broken in peeces as a Potters veſſell, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p n="47">47. Laſtly, to adde no more, Whether the Kingdom of <hi>Glory</hi> hereafter to be enjoyed in <hi>Heaven,</hi> be not the proper State in which <hi>God</hi> hath appointed the <hi>Saints</hi> to live <hi>immediatly</hi> in <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi> without the uſe of <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and not the Kingdome of <hi>Grace</hi> here on earth, in which the Saints are <hi>imperfect,</hi> and ſee the Lord (for the moſt part) through a <hi>glaſſe darkly, knowing but in part, and propheſying but in part, till that which is perfect be come,</hi> according to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9, 10, 11, 12. and the Apoſtles owne judgement of himſelfe, <hi>Phil</hi> 3.13, 14. And whether to hold the contrary, be not to confound thoſe two States of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> which the Scriptures doe diſtinguiſh, ſo that the caſting off the uſe of <hi>Divine Inſtitutions,</hi> and <hi>Goſpel-ordinances,</hi> and <hi>Duties</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> appointed for beleevers to walk in the practiſe of, till the Lord Jeſus Chriſts comming again, muſt of neceſſity be lookt upon as having no <hi>bottome</hi> on the ſacred Scriptures, but a viſion of mens own <hi>brains,</hi> and deceitfull <hi>hearts,</hi> directly contrary to the <hi>Faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. Jude, v. 3, 4.</note> and therefore of all thoſe that love the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity, juſtly to be condemned and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:165014:17"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX By way of Poſt-ſcript, To all thoſe whom the former Conſiderations doe more eſpecially concerne.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU have ſeen, (or <hi>may ſee</hi>) what that <hi>Balm</hi> is, which I have (as a weak inſtrument in the hands of Chriſt the great Phyſitian of Souls) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to powre forth in the former Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, for the healing of your wounded ſoules: And you have alſo ſeen (or <hi>may ſee</hi>) in my Epiſtle to the Reader, what my grounds and ends have been in ſo doing; ſo that (I doubt not) but you will look upon me as one that hath had <hi>nothing</hi> in my eye, but the <hi>honour</hi> of Chriſt, and <hi>welfare</hi> of your ſoules. If the buſines I have undertaken, had not been of great importance and concernment, I had not (I aſſure you) put pen to paper, but when I ſaw the <hi>ſad effects</hi> were like to attend this opinion and practice of yours, by intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing a ſpirituall <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> in the Kingdome of Chriſt, and threatning <hi>Ruine</hi> to all the true and <hi>right conſtituted</hi> Churches in the world, I could not but<note n="a" place="margin">Principiis obſta, ſerò me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicina paratur, Cum mala per longa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luere moras.</note> make haſte (according to the<note n="b" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.7.</note> meaſure of the gift of Chriſt vouchſafed to me) towards the preventing of them. If I have ſpoken or written none other then the words of <hi>Truth and Soberneſſe,</hi> I ſhall deſire you in the name of him, who is <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelfe (our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt) to ſubſcribe thereunto: If otherwiſe, I truſt by the <hi>ſame
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:165014:18"/>grace</hi> received, I ſhall be ready to ſee it, and acknowledge it whenſoever it ſhall be made out unto me: onely I ſhall deſire, that the ſame<note n="c" place="margin">Apud Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae Alumnos non ad humanas rationes &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitationes diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendae ſunt res divinae; ſed ad ſenſum &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae ſpiritus, oratio inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretatio<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodanda. <hi>Juſt. Mart.</hi> Neque te quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diſſerentem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinuiſſemus, niſi cuncta ad ſeripturas re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fcrres; inde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones adducere ſtudio tibi eſt. <hi>id. ibid. Dial. cum Triphon.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>medium,</hi> viz. the holy Scriptures of God, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the old and new Teſtament, which I have endeavoured to uſe in the former conſiderations, may be uſed by ſuch as ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſuch a work. But becauſe I may ſave that labour in order to your further and greater ſatisfaction, I have thought it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to doe ſomething by way of anſwering thoſe objections, or removing thoſe grounds, upon which (I ſuppoſe) all of you, (or at leaſt) many of you, doe build your practice of renouncing and caſting off the uſe of Ordinances and religious Duties.</p>
            <p>Now I ſuppoſe the <hi>grounds</hi> upon which you build the caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off the uſe of Ordinances, may be reduced to theſe eight Heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That a perſon may doe well enough, and comfortably enjoy himſelfe without the uſe of Ordinances, as hearing the Word, Prayer, breaking of bread in a communion of Saints, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That the ſucceſſe of things doth not depend upon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of Duties and Ordinances, but on Gods eternall purpoſe and decree.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That God knowes our wants, and ſtands not in need of any of our performances, to move him to the helping and ſatisfying of us.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>That many have uſed Ordinances, and performed Duties, but to ſmall purpoſe, and thoſe that doe uſe them, are little the better.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>That Ordinances are but poore low Diſpenſations, and not ſo conſiſtent with a Beleevers living in God, that is altogether above Ordinances, and that God doth uſe to lead his people from Goſpel-formes, to a more immediate enjoyment of himſelfe in the Spirit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>That none are to pray or perform Duties at any time, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they are moved thereunto by the Spirit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. <hi>That the uſe of Ordinances is more Legall then Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and engenders to bondage rather then liberty, looking more to a covenant of works then grace, the Goſpel requiring beleeving not working.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8 <hi>Another ground upon which people build their caſting off the uſe of Word and Ordinances, is this, Becauſe the Word and Ordinances are nothing without the Spirit. They can never work
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:165014:18"/>any impreſſion upon the ſoule, or acquaint the Spirit of a man or woman, that the Lord is his God, or that Chriſt is his Saviour, &amp;c. but this belongs to the office of the Spirit of God; the Word and Ordinances of themſelves are never able to work ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in the ſoule.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9. <hi>That there are many places in the new Teſtament, which hodl forth the non-performance of duties, and laying aſide the uſe of Ordinances, as</hi> Heb. 8.11. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.22, 23. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe are the grounds upon which people build their leaving and caſting off of Ordinances, ſome of them reſpect thoſe that are meere <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and others reſpect ſuch as pretend to the <hi>greateſt perfection</hi> of holineſſe attainable in this life, I ſhall (by the help of Chriſt) make anſwer to them all, as they are laid downe, in order to the diſcoverie of the unſoundneſſe of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Touching the firſt of the former grounds, upon which peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple build the caſting off the uſe of the holy Ordinances of Chriſt, and duties of religion, it was this, <hi>That a perſon may doe well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, &amp;c. without the uſe of them.</hi> Now in anſwer to this, for the diſcovery of the <hi>unſoundneſſe</hi> of it, I utterly deny it, and affirme the contrary, that ſuch as caſt off the uſe of Ordinances,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.22.</note> or live in the neglect of them, <hi>cannot poſſibly</hi> doe ſo well, nor ſo <hi>comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably</hi> enjoy themſelves in the neglect, as they might if they did <hi>conſcionably</hi> performe them, and my reaſon for it is this (which I conceive is ungainſayable) Becauſe whatſoever ſuch doe enjoy in order to their welfare and proſperity here in this world, though in the greateſt fulneſſe, they doe not enjoy it with the bleſſing and favour of God, they may enjoy them, but not comfortably, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not through a promiſe, nor by vertue of having intereſt in Chriſt, through whom all our enjoyments become bleſsed to us, and without whom all good things become evill and accurſed to us.</p>
            <p>Now ſuch cannot poſſibly enjoy their good things through Chriſt &amp; a promiſe, that neglect prayer, &amp;c (&amp; ſo by conſequence not enjoy them nor themſelvs comfortably) becauſe thoſe mercies that come to us <hi>through a promiſe,</hi> and by vertue of our intereſt in Chriſt, they come in the <hi>way of Prayer,</hi> and the uſe of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; for the ſame God that hath made a promiſe to be our God, and to make us bleſſed in the enjoyment of himſelfe and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:165014:19"/>hath alſo ſaid, that he will be <hi>ſought unto</hi> for all thoſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, before we ſhall enjoy them, as <hi>Ezek,</hi> 36.37. And when a perſon is once in Chriſt, his being in Chriſt doth not take him off from duties, but rather puts him upon the <hi>diligent</hi> performance of them. And hence it is, that the Spirit of Chriſt that dwells in beleevers, is called a Spirit <hi>of prayer and ſupplication, Rom</hi> 8.15.26. <hi>Gal</hi> 4.6. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12, 10. And Chriſt hath promiſed beleevers to grant them their deſires upon their asking his Father in his name <hi>John</hi> 14. and 15. and 16. chapters, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.7. with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places to the ſame purpoſe, and hereupon he enjoynes belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to watch and pray, and ask neceſſaries daily at the hands of God their Father, for the good both of their bodies and ſoules, their temporall and eternall welfare, <hi>Matth</hi> 6.11, 12. So that 'tis not faith in Chriſt, and a promiſe, that in it ſelfe ſimply conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, makes us partakers and poſſeſſors of the good things of God with comfort, but faith <hi>exerciſed,</hi> and <hi>put forth</hi> in prayer, and uſe of holy Duties and Ordinances of worſhip. Faith in Chriſt, and the covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> layes claime to the good things of God, yea God himſelfe (bleſſed for ever) is his <hi>Portion,</hi> but <hi>Prayer</hi> fetcheth them in to the ſoule, through Jeſus Chriſts mediation. And therefore as perſons living in the neglect of duties, diſcover themſelves to be deſtitute of the Spirit of Chriſt, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of true faith in Chriſt, ſo they manifeſt themſelves to have no <hi>true right</hi> to what they enjoy as men and women in Chriſt, nor to have them in mercy from God, or in a capacity to enjoy a holy and ſanctified uſe of them, but are under all with the curſe of God upon them, ſo that as the wiſe man ſaith, the <hi>very proſperity of ſuch fooles deſtroyeth them,</hi> Prov. 1.32.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ground upon which people build their neglect of duties, and caſting off ordinances, is the <hi>Eternall purpoſes and decrees of God,</hi> who hath by them appointed how things ſhall be, and there is no altering of them, by our faſting, praying, &amp;c. or performing any duties of worſhip whatſoever. Shall wee think (ſay ſome) that the judgement of the <hi>Sword, Peſtilence,</hi> and <hi>Famine</hi> that walked up and down the Kingdome, as the <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners</hi> of divine Juſtice in an uncontrollable manner have been (in ſo great and wonderfull meaſure) removed from the prayers and ſupplications of any or all the Saints in <hi>England,</hi> and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the <hi>predeterminate</hi> Councell and decrees of God.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That the <hi>Decrees</hi> of God doe not exclude
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:165014:19"/>in the leaſt, the <hi>uſe of the means</hi> towards the effecting &amp; bringing about of them, but as God hath determined in his eternall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels what he will doe for the good of any of his people, ſo he hath alſo determined that the <hi>means</hi> ſhall be uſed for the obtaining it: Yea, we finde in Scripture, that this is made a certain ſigne that God hath determined to do us ſome great good, when he <hi>ſtirreth up</hi> our hearts to be earneſt with him in prayer, and the uſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lawfull meanes for the obtaining it, as we may ſee in <hi>Daniel</hi> 9.2, compared with <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12, 13, 14. where we finde in theſe two Scriptures, two things to our preſent purpoſe, 1. That God had purpoſed the deliverance of his people from their <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byloniſh</hi> captivity, after 70. yeares were expired. 2. That he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed alſo, and foretold by <hi>Jeremy,</hi> that neare about the expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe 70. yeares, a <hi>Spirit of Prayer</hi> ſhould bee given to them, and they ſhould goe and pray unto the Lord for their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance; and hereupon <hi>Daniel</hi> is ſtirred up about the end of thoſe 70. yeares, to a more then ordinary ſeeking to God by <hi>faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and prayer,</hi> for the accompliſhing of his promiſe, as is cleare from <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.3. and how much is the Lord taken with it, <hi>verſe</hi> 20, 21, 22, 23. ſo that we may from hence eaſily ſee, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and purpoſes of God, <hi>doe not exclude</hi> the performance of prayer, and uſe of holy ordinances, but rather <hi>include</hi> them: not that they are <hi>deſerving cauſes</hi> of our mercies, but onely ſuch <hi>wayes and means</hi> as God hath in his wiſdome appointed (in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the manifeſtation of our duty towards him) without which he will not vouchſafe us our deſires. And hence it is alſo, that we find the practice of the Saints hath been manifeſted this way, by ſeeking to God in the way and uſe of his ordinances, for their enjoyment both of mercies <hi>Spirituall</hi> and <hi>Temporal,</hi> as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures abundantly declare and teſtifie.</p>
            <p>And whereas many think, that the uſe of <hi>ſecond cauſes,</hi> and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary meanes naturally, are ſufficient to attain their deſires with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the uſe of prayer, &amp;c. becauſe God hath given a power, or naturall force to <hi>ſecond cauſes</hi> to doe us good, as <hi>fire to heat us, meat to nouriſh us, cloathes to warm us, reaſon to guide us, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to keep us in health, and cure us of diſeaſes, &amp;c.</hi> I wil evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prove from the Scriptures, that the Lord hath put his ſervants upon the <hi>practice of prayer</hi> to ſeek his bleſſing and directions in the <hi>uſe of all theſe,</hi> yea, in ſuch <hi>naturall, civill,</hi> and <hi>morall things</hi> and <hi>actions,</hi> wherein all men have <hi>freedome of will,</hi> and want nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:165014:20"/>ordinary meanes to help themſelves, nor wiſdome and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding naturally to guide them. As for inſtance, 1. <hi>in the uſe of food,</hi> though there be therein a <hi>naturall vertue</hi> put and placed by God to nouriſh us, yet we finde how the ſervants of God have uſed prayer to deſire the Lord to bleſſe that unto them, as Chriſt himſelfe frequently, when he took bread he looked up to heaven and prayed for a bleſſing on it, and ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> and many others, according to 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5, 6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the <hi>undertaking of Journeyes,</hi> how was the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> carried out by prayer to the Lord, for his direction, as in 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Now God himſelf, and our Father, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, direct our way unto you.</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.10. And thus <hi>Ezra</hi> in his journey towards <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael that came out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> earneſtly ſought the Lord for a <hi>right way</hi> Ezra 8.21, 22, 23.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the <hi>making of marriages,</hi> how did <hi>Eleazer, Abrahams</hi> ſervant, (though he were an <hi>underſtanding man,</hi> and very able to manage his buſineſſe he went about) earneſtly <hi>ſupplicate God</hi> for direction and ſucceſſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.12. where we finde, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he attempted his work, he <hi>ſought the Lord</hi> to give him good ſpeed, as knowing that ſuch in buſineſſes as theſe, though but of leſſer importance, the way to become proſperous was to <hi>ſeeke to the Lord</hi> for direction and good ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the actions <hi>of our common Tradings</hi> and ordinary em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, the Lords people have deſired God to bleſſe and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per them, as knowing that it is not ſo much their <hi>naturall actions,</hi> and <hi>diligent endeavours</hi> that makes them rich and proſperous, as the <hi>bleſſing</hi> of God. And if there were no inſtances at all to be given, yet the command of God is ſo cleare for it, that it may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly ſatisfie thoſe that are <hi>ingenuous,</hi> as that of <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.6. <hi>In all thy wayes acknowledge him, and he ſhall direct thy paths</hi> And <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6, 7. <hi>Be carefull for nothing,</hi> that is, in reſpect of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, or iſſue, or ſucceſſe of things, but <hi>in every thing, mark</hi> in every thing <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by <hi>prayer and ſupplication with thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving let your requeſts be made known unto God.</hi> And then this will follow, that the <hi>peace of God ſhall keep our hearts and mindes through Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> as if there were no true peace to be enjoyed where there is a neglect of a perſons duty this way.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third ground upon which people build their caſting off
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:165014:20"/>the uſe of religious duties and ordinances, is taken from <hi>Gods knowing of all our wants,</hi> and his <hi>readineſſe to ſupply them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our ſeeking to him:</hi> for ſay they, God hath no need of our prayers and performances to move him to doe us good.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that though this be a truth, yet the <hi>infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> men make from it in caſting off the performance of duties, is not good, but weake and idle; for firſt of all, though God know our wants better then we our ſelves doe, yet he hath made it known to us in the Scriptures, that it is his will wee ſhould ſpread them before him in prayer, &amp;c. as <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. <hi>In every thing let your requeſts be made</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>known,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, and that by prayer and ſupplication, now this cannot be meant of making known theſe requeſts <hi>to any other</hi> then unto God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he alone is able to ſupply us, to heare and help us. So <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.11, 12. &amp; 7.7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.37.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though God ſtand not in need of our prayers and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, yet he will have us to perform them that wee may the better know our duties, and how much we are beholding to him who is the alone <hi>Author and Donor</hi> of all our enjoyments. And hence it is that he would have his people of old to put him in <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance,</hi> and <hi>declare that they might be juſtified, Eſay</hi> 43.26. not that <hi>Jehovah</hi> is <hi>forgetful,</hi> or ſtands in need of a <hi>Monitor,</hi> as it is too too frequently with poor creatures like our ſelves. No; but that we might <hi>know our duties,</hi> and conſider from whom all our mercies <hi>flow,</hi> and to whom all our <hi>Returnes</hi> of praiſe ought to be made.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Although the bleſſed <hi>Nature</hi> of God in Jeſus Chriſt be infinitly carried out with readineſſe &amp; for wardneſſe towards the helping of poore creatures in and under all their wants and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, yet our ſeeking for this help, doth not in the leaſt <hi>derogate</hi> from the glory of his goodneſſe, but rather advance it. My rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for it, are theſe: 1. Becauſe it is a moſt evident <hi>Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to Heaven and Earth, that he is gentle and eaſie to be intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, full of bowels of compaſſion, rich to all that call upon him, even to the young <hi>Ravens</hi> when they cry, as the Pſalmiſt ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.9. And me thinks there is a great <hi>Emphaſis</hi> in the word <hi>[Cry,]</hi> as thereby noting to us, how gracious and full of compaſſion the <hi>Nature</hi> of God is, which could not be ſo well diſcerned, if there were not ſuch <hi>Cryes</hi> put up from poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to him: So that the drawings forth of thoſe tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:165014:21"/>which are in God, by the cryes of his poore creatures to him, doe exceedingly ſpeak: out and commend to men and Angels, the unconceivable goodneſſe of his <hi>Nature.</hi> 2. Becauſe the Lords pleaſure, that we ſhould firſt ſeek him, before we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy mercies from him, is a great <hi>Argument</hi> of this ſingular love to us. And this is evident from hence: 1. In that it is from the great delight he hath to behold and heare the work of his owne Spirit in us, making interceſſion with ſighes and groanes that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utterable, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.14. 2. becauſe he knowes that his mercies and bleſſings will be a great deale the <hi>ſweeter</hi> to us, when we have got them in the way of prayer, as we finde they were to <hi>David, Daniel,</hi> and other of the Saints. And this the Saints find by <hi>experience,</hi> that thoſe mercies which are gotten in a way of faith and prayer, (through much wreſtling with God, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to honour him by beleeving) are farre <hi>ſweeter</hi> to us then thoſe that come to us in a common and ordinary way of generall <hi>Providence,</hi> and coſt us nothing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth ground upon which people build their leaving the uſe of Ordinances, is this, that <hi>they themſelves have uſed Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and performed duties, but to ſmall purpoſe, and thoſe that doe uſe them, are little the better by uſing of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, 1. As concerning themſelves, whether they have not oftentimes diſcovered the contrary, beleeving that they have enjoyed very much of God at ſuch times, when they have been in the uſe of Ordinance, as in <hi>Prayer, hearing the word, communion with the Saints, &amp;c.</hi> ſaying with <hi>David, O how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable are thy Tabernacles! my ſoule longeth, yea even fainteth for the Courts of thy Houſe, Pſal.</hi> 84.1, 2. And with <hi>Peter</hi> when he was with Chriſt in Mount Tabor, <hi>It is good to be here, let us build here three Tabernacles Matth.</hi> 17.4. This, I ſay, and <hi>much more,</hi> have thoſe ſaid and ſpoken, that now caſt off Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. If they plaid the <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> and were not reall in what they did, but ſuffered their tongues to ſpeake more then their hearts felt, they muſt blame themſelves, and not finde fault with the <hi>Ordinances.</hi> Beſides, doth the grace of God (wrought in any ſoule) teach them to lay the fault of their <hi>unfruitfulneſſe</hi> and <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe</hi> on the <hi>meanes,</hi> Chriſt hath inſtituted to make them fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full? Are not ſuch reaſonings <hi>carnall and fleſhly,</hi> and not from the Spirit, which ſuch perſons pretend to be wholly caught up to live and walk in. Why may not a ſicke and diſeaſed perſon,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:165014:21"/>that lies under the <hi>predominancy</hi> of corrupt <hi>humours</hi> in his ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, complain as well, that the ground of his diſtemper pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from his <hi>food</hi> which he eates (which is excellent good, and full of ſweet nouriſhment in it ſelfe) and not from the <hi>ſuper fluity</hi> of corrupt humours in his ſtomack. Therefore I ſhould advice ſuch perſons as blame the ſacred ordinances of Chriſt, to reflect back on themſelves, &amp; ſee the ground of all their <hi>unprofitableneſſe</hi> in their own hearts. And whereas ſome ſay, that they have often prayed, but to ſmall purpoſe; for they have ſeen it hath been all one to them and with them, when they have, or have not prayed, I would fain know whether this be not the very <hi>garb</hi> and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the <hi>Wicked,</hi> as the Scripture abundantly mentioneth, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> 58.3. <hi>Wherefore have we faſted,</hi> ſay they, <hi>and thou ſeeſt it not? Wherefore have we afflicted our ſoule, and thou takeſt no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it?</hi> And therefore it ſeemes in the Prophet <hi>Malachies</hi> dayes, they reſolve to leave praying, <hi>Malach.</hi> 3.14. <hi>It is in vain,</hi> ſay they, <hi>to ſerve God, and what profit is it unto us?</hi> Hippoctitas cannot endure to <hi>wait</hi> on the Lord, but like the King of <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, What ſhould I wait on the Lord any longer?</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6. <hi>ult.</hi> whereas thoſe that are true worſhippers of God, (though they may at ſome times <hi>through temptation</hi> be <hi>ſhaken</hi> in their <hi>confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> and conſequently be taken off from drawing nigh to God in duties for a ſeaſon, yet) their hearts <hi>fall not foule</hi> with the duty, but rather with their own <hi>corruption,</hi> and are ſtill preſſing on af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter further communion with God, and greater enjoyment of him in the duties of his worſhip, and are reſolved to <hi>wait</hi> on the Lord in a way of ſeeking his face, through the ſtrength of Chriſt, and not to give him reſt till hee hath <hi>returned</hi> to them, and ſpoken peace to their ſoules. The Saints know that the Lord hath <hi>graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ends</hi> in deferring to anſwer and help them when they cry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and that they ſhall be no <hi>loſers</hi> by their waiting on God, and therefore keep on ſeeking and waiting, though the Lord doe not forthwith heare and anſwer them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As for that concernes others, that <hi>ſuch as uſe Ordinances, and are daily in the practice of prayer, &amp;c.</hi> are (for ought they can ſee) <hi>little the better for them:</hi> I anſwer, if they mean <hi>Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> and carnall Goſpellers, that have a meere <hi>form</hi> of godlineſſe onely, but want the power of it in their hearts and lives, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee denied but ſo it is, yet no reaſon in the leaſt, why the blame ſhould be laid on the <hi>Ordinances,</hi> or that any that are <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:165014:22"/>in their walking w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> God, ſhould <hi>ceaſe</hi> the uſing of them: for the <hi>abuſe</hi> of what is lawfull by ſome, is no ſufficient reaſon why others ſhould bee taken off from the uſe of it. Meat and drink, and recreations, with other things that are lawfull and good in themſelves, may be abuſed oftentimes by ſome that ſeeke after nothing more then the ſatisfying of their carnall luſts; yet that may not take off others from the moderate uſe of them. And ſo 'tis here in the poynt of Ordinances; we may as well reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Demas,</hi> with others, abuſed their profeſſion of Chriſt, therefore none are to make profeſſion of him.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, if it be ſpoken of all in the generall, thoſe that are upright before God in their performances and uſe of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, as well as thoſe that are meere formaliſts, then I demand of ſuch, whether <hi>living in God</hi> (who is <hi>Love</hi> it ſelfe) can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly lead them forth to ſuch wayes of <hi>uncharitable</hi> judging their brethren. It's true, that the <hi>beſt</hi> of the Saints may not live and walk up ſo <hi>exactly</hi> to thoſe performances of duties and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of holy Ordinances as were to be wiſhed; I plead not for the <hi>unprofitableneſſe of any</hi> under the meanes of grace: but, that <hi>none</hi> of them are fruitful, nor growing up to fuller enjoyments of God in Chriſt, through the Spirit, in the uſe of Ordinances and holy Duties, <hi>this I deny,</hi> as a groſſe and <hi>foule</hi> untruth, having <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience</hi> to the contrary in many of the ſervants of God through rich mercie. And I am <hi>confident</hi> of it, if thoſe that now <hi>caſt off</hi> Ordinances, could look with a <hi>clearer &amp; ſtronger</hi> eye of <hi>love</hi> and <hi>charity</hi> in thoſe that make uſe of them, and could beleeve that they live in the uſe of Ordinances (not <hi>formally</hi> and <hi>cuſtomarily,</hi> as the men of the world that place their greateſt religion in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of them, but out of <hi>pure conſcience,</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> to the commands of Chriſt, and from higher and more noble <hi>principles</hi> and <hi>ends,</hi> then Hypocrites or carnall Goſpellers can poſſibly put forth and manifeſt) they would not cry down the uſe of Goſpel-ordinances, nor <hi>judge thoſe</hi> for poore, low, weake Chriſtians, that uſe them as now they doe. But (through an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded and unchriſtian <hi>jealouſie</hi> that is entertained by them touching others, together with an <hi>high</hi> and over-weening con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of themſelves) it is to be feared they are ſo offended with or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and ſpeak ſo contemptibly and undervaluingly of thoſe that uſe them, I ſhall ſay no more to ſuch, on this particular, but wiſh them to be cloathed with humility, and better to ſtudy the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:165014:22"/>
               <hi>grounds</hi> of their own <hi>leaving</hi> ordinances, before they call into queſtion their <hi>brethrens,</hi> in the uſe of them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The fifth ground upon which people build their neglect of Duties, and caſting off <hi>Ordinances,</hi> is this: That they <hi>look upon Ordinances, and Duties of worſhip,</hi> as <hi>Prayer, Preaching, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Seales, Church-fellowſhip, &amp;c. as poore, low diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, weake formes, childiſh things,</hi> and ſuch as be not ſo <hi>conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> with a <hi>perſons living in God, &amp;c.</hi> but out of which God doth <hi>lead</hi> his people to a more <hi>immediate enjoyment</hi> of himſelfe in the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Now for anſwer to this, Firſt, I deſire it may bee ſeriouſly conſidered, Whether the <hi>Ordinances</hi> and <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> of the <hi>great God,</hi> and our Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> are <hi>low things, poore, weake, childiſh diſpenſations;</hi> Are thoſe low and childiſh things, in which the <hi>glory</hi> of Chriſts <hi>Wiſdome, Power,</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſſe</hi> doth ſhine forth? And are not the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> &amp; divine <hi>Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Chriſt held forth in them, ſuch <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations?</hi> How then darepoore ſinfull duſt and aſhes thus reaſon and argue? Is it not rather a cleare <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> that ſuch men and women as thus ſpeak, have <hi>low</hi> and baſe <hi>thoughts</hi> of Chriſt in the managing of that great buſines his Father hath intruſted him with, about the <hi>ordering and governing</hi> his Houſe &amp; Kingdome. Let that of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7, 8.9, 10, 11. be ſeriouſly weighed, and then tell me whether the <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> of Chriſt under the New Teſtament, be low things and <hi>childiſh.</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the former place ſhewes clearly that the very diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Legall</hi> Covenant miniſtery and ordinances, was<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, but how much more then (ſaith he) muſt the <hi>Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> Covenant miniſtery and ordinances under the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be glorious? If the miniſtration or diſpenſation of <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Condemnation</hi> under the Law, and that which was to be <hi>done away,</hi> was glorious, how much more the <hi>Miniſtration</hi> and <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> of the Spirit under the Goſpel, which is <hi>perpetuall,</hi> &amp; to remain, ſo that we ſee that the Diſpenſations of Chriſt under the New Teſtament, are all <hi>glorious things:</hi> and if ſo, how dare any ſpeak ſo <hi>diſgraeefully</hi> of them, as to call them <hi>poore, low, weake childiſh things?</hi> Doubtleſſe the Lord Jeſus will give men and women but little thankes for thoſe * <hi>hard</hi> ſpeeches of theirs they have uttered againſt him,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> at his comming to execute judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon all ungodly ones, <hi>Jude Epiſt. v.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:165014:23"/>Beſides, I deſire ſuch perſons as ſpeak ſo <hi>ignominiouſly</hi> of the Lord Jeſus, ordinances, and Goſpel-inſtitutions, would but an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer mee, or rather the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to theſe few de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Is the Name of the great and glorious <hi>Jehovah</hi> a low and meane, a poore and childiſh thing, and is not his <hi>Worſhip</hi> his name?</item>
               <item>2. Is the <hi>publiſhing</hi> and bearing forth his <hi>Name</hi> before the world, a low and childiſh thing, and is not the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> of the Goſpel ſo much? <hi>Acts</hi> 9.15.</item>
               <item>3 Is the ſanctifying this great &amp; glorious <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Iehovah,</hi> a low &amp; childiſh thing? And do not the Saints do ſo much, when they drw <hi>nigh to God</hi> in the performance of the duties of his <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? Lev.</hi> 10.3.</item>
               <item>4. Is <hi>Glory</hi> a low thing, and not worth the looking after, and is not <hi>Mount Syon</hi> and all the holy Aſſemblies ſo ſtiled? <hi>Eſay</hi> 4.5. &amp; 60.7.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In a word, are not all the <hi>Veſſels</hi> of the Lords ſpirituall Temple and Houſe under the New Teſtament, <hi>clean and holy?</hi> And ſhall we call that <hi>common</hi> and unclean that the eternall God, the King of <hi>Sion</hi> hath cleanſed and ſanctified? As Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter, Act.</hi> 10.15. ſo may I ſay to ſuch men, Cal not thoſe things common and unclean that the Lord Jeſus (the great Judge of quicke and dead) hath cleanſed and ſanctified, and ſet apart for his uſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, call not the ordinances and inſtitutions with the holy Saints and ſervants of Chriſt (that are called out of the world to make uſe of them, in order to the lifting up of the glory of their Lord and Maſter, their Head and Husband) poore, low, weak things. If Chriſt will <hi>own</hi> them, and <hi>honour</hi> them, let men take heed how they deſpiſe and <hi>diſhonour</hi> them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas it is ſaid, that the uſe of ſuch Goſpel-ordinances and Inſtitutions of worſhip, are not <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with a perſons li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in God, I utterly deny it; &amp; my reaſon for it is this, becauſe thoſe things that are <hi>ſubordinate</hi> in their nature one to another, may very well ſtand together without <hi>confounding</hi> and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another: And ſo is it here, <hi>Divine</hi> ordinances of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as <hi>Prayer, Preaching, hearing, communion with the Saints at the Lords Supper, &amp;c.</hi> are <hi>ſubordinate</hi> wayes and meanes which Chriſt hath appointed to <hi>further</hi> (not <hi>hinder</hi>) a beleevers living in God. And the more the Saints are in the uſe of thoſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:165014:23"/>
               <hi>meanes,</hi> with upright and ſpirituall hearts, the more they are <hi>fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered</hi> therein. Indeed living in God, and living in ordinances, cannot ſtand together, becauſe a perſon cannot give his heart to two lovers at once; but living in God, and <hi>uſing</hi> of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as meanes in order to the enjoyment of the end, may very well ſtand together. As for example, A perſon that depends on God for his naturall life, eats and drinkes, and ſleeps, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and takes phyſick, and uſeth theſe and other like meanes, in order to the preſervation of that life, and the uſe of theſe meanes doth not null or make void his faith in, or dependance on God. Indeed <hi>placing</hi> our life, joy, comfort, excellency in theſe, and putting our confidence in them, cannot ſtand with a perſons <hi>living in,</hi> or depending on God, becauſe it is to make them our gods, &amp; not the Lord; but where there is only a <hi>conſcientious</hi> uſe of them in obedience to the will of God, and in order to the furthering of his providence, there a perſon may bee ſaid to live in God, and depend on him, very well notwithſtanding his uſe of theſe. And thus it is in reſpect of a Chriſtians ſpirituall life, he lives in God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone through Chriſt, and makes him alone the Reſt and Center of his Soule, and yet makes uſe of <hi>Prayer, Preaching, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Scriptures, fellowſhip with the Saints, &amp;c.</hi> as the meanes which Chriſt hath appointed in order thereunto. And therefore what can be plainer then this that we affirme, <hi>viz.</hi> that living in God, and uſing of Ordinances, are <hi>conſiſtent,</hi> and may well ſtand together. And what horrible wickedneſſe and <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> is it in<note n="*" place="margin">I charge not all, but ſome more eſpecially, that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of this opinion and practice, who are grown very looſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane in their worſhip.</note> many of thoſe that deny the uſe of Ordinances, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that living in God, and uſing of ordinances and duties, are not ſo conſiſtent, when they can grant, that living in God, and <hi>dicing, drinking, dancing, drabbing, &amp;c.</hi> (with divers other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations that are done of them in <hi>ſecret,</hi> and too too openly, that a man may be a ſhamed to mention, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.12.) are conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent, and may very well ſtand together. But, <hi>ô tempora! ô mores!</hi> Oh the deſperate wickedneſſe of men and women in this Age! Can the wayes and workes of darkneſſe that the Lord hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, ſtand with a perſons living in God <hi>(which is ſuch a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous abomination, as hell it ſelfe can hardly afford a fouler)</hi> and cannot the wayes and works of righteouſneſſe and godlineſſe, the ſerving and worſhipping of God, ſtand with living in God? O quinteſſence of impiety. <hi>thou child of the Devill, thou enemy of all righteouſneſſe, wilt thou not ceaſe to pervert the right wayes
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:165014:24"/>of the Lord?</hi> Acts 13.10. <hi>What ſhall be given unto thee, or what ſhall be done unto thee, thou falſe tongue? Sharp Arrowes of the mighty, with coales of Iuniper,</hi> Pſal. 120.2, 3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whereas they ſay, That <hi>God doth uſe to lead his people out of thoſe low and childiſh diſpenſations, to a more high enjoyment of Himſelfe:</hi> I anſwer briefly, Is it not a childiſh reaſoning to ſay, God leads children from their childiſh <hi>words</hi> and <hi>actions</hi> they manifeſt whiles they are children, therefore hee leads them from <hi>ſpeaking,</hi> and <hi>reaſoning,</hi> and <hi>diſcourſing,</hi> and <hi>ſtudying,</hi> and other actions that belong to a <hi>rationall</hi> creature when they grow old: So here, what <hi>weakneſſe</hi> doe men diſcover to the world, when they ſay, God leads his people out of the uſe of ordinances, and wayes of worſhiping and ſerving of him, by prayer, &amp;c. when he leads them out from their <hi>ignorance, darkneſſe, fleſhli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, filthineſſe, carnalneſſe,</hi> that was wont to cleave to, and bee mixed with their performances. Becauſe God leads his people out of <hi>living in,</hi> and <hi>truſting to</hi> their meat and drink, and other creature-comforts and enjoyments, to which their hearts are apt and prone to <hi>bow down;</hi> therefore he leads them out, and takes them off from <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking,</hi> and uſe of creature-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts: what <hi>madneſſe</hi> would it be in any man to affirme this? So here, becauſe God is pleaſed to take off his people more and more from their <hi>unbeliefe, pride,</hi> ſelfe-ſeekng, &amp;c, and other <hi>weakneſſes and ſinnes,</hi> in the performance of the duties of his worſhip, therefore hee leades them out of, and from the duties themſelves; Is not this <hi>handſome reaſoning.</hi> Beſides, how can it poſſibly be, that God ſhould lead the Saints from the uſe of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, when he hath ordained the perpetuall uſe of them to his Saints in all ages, as I have ſhewed in the <hi>Quaeries.</hi> Hee leads his people indeed to live above them, but not to live without them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The ſixth ground on which people build their neglect of Duties, &amp;c. is this, <hi>That none are bound to pray, or performe Duties,, &amp;c. further then the Spirit moves them thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I anſwer in the firſt place, That though this be a <hi>Truth</hi> in ſomeſenſe, yet we ſhould take heed how we<note n="*" place="margin">Though wee are to goe when Gods Spirit moves us, yet are we not to neglect when wee doe not perceive ſuch ſenſible moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. &amp;c. <hi>Bolt. Bounds of Chriſtian freedome, v. 202.</hi> We muſt doe duty ſometime out of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, although we want both a heart to it, and a heart in it. <hi>Id. ibid.</hi>
               </note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it, and make a wrong uſe of it, to bring about <hi>thoſe ends</hi> for which it was never intended, as this in particular for one, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>willing omiſſion, and witting neglect of the duties of Gods worſhip both publick and ſecret,</hi> which he calls us <hi>daily</hi> to the performance of. It is true, as the Spirit of Chriſt is the <hi>efficient
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:165014:24"/>cauſe</hi> of ſpirituall life in beleevers (<hi>without whom we can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, Iohn</hi> 15.5.) and works the grace of <hi>Sanctification</hi> in their hearts, ſo there is <hi>no performing</hi> of holy duties without him: But whether a beleever ſo ſanctified and enlivened by the Holy Ghoſt, is not to<note n="*" place="margin">Though wee cannot bring the Spirit to us, yet let us ſet our ſelves in the way for him, to meet with us. <hi>Hold up the performance of duty, &amp;c. Id. ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>enter</hi> upon religious duties, before the Spirit put forth a new act of ſpirituall life in him, I ſuppoſe can hardly be made out: For I ſuppoſe after Regeneration, or the new Birth, when a perſon is <hi>implanted,</hi> or incorporated into Chriſt, he is not to be lookt upon as a <hi>meere paſſive</hi> in the performance of holy duties, as <hi>Prayer, Mortification of ſinne, &amp;c.</hi> but as a <hi>worker together</hi> with God. And ſo much thoſe eminently anoynted and qualified ſervants of Chriſt, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Tho. Goodwin,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Ieremy Burronghes,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>W. Greenhill</hi> affirme. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Tho. Goodwin</hi> in his<note n="*" place="margin">Treatiſe of the tryall of a Chriſtians growth, p. 82, 83. &amp; 138, 139.</note> Treatiſe quoted in the Margent touching a beleevers <hi>Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying ſinne,</hi> ſaith, <q>We are purged from ſin as the body is by Phyſick from humours; though the Phyſick work, yet Nature joynes with the Phyſick, being quickned and helped by it, to caſt out the humours: ſo as the meanes whereby God purgeth us, are not to bee imagined to doe it, as meere Phyſicall A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, like as the pruning-hook cuts off branches from the Tree, or as when a Chyrurgion cuts out dead fleſh; but theſe meanes doe it by ſtirring up our graces, and quickning them, and by ſetting our thoughts, and faith, and affections a-worke, and ſo God aſſiſting with the power of Chriſts death, he doth purge us daily, by making his word, afflictions, &amp;c. for to ſet our thoughts on work againſt ſinn. It is certain, that unleſſe our thoughts work on the meanes, as well as the meanes work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and ſo mingle themſelves with them; unleſſe Faith and Chriſts death bee mingled in the heart, it purgeth not: And therefore it is ſaid, we purge our ſelves, as 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. and 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.3. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. Wee by the Spirit mortifie the deeds of the fleſh, this is ſaid (ſaith hee) as well as that God purgeth us, becauſe God ſtill in going on to purge us, doth it by ſtirring up our graces, and uſeth therein acts of our faith, and love, and many motives and conſiderations to doe it.</q> Thus this <hi>pretious</hi> ſervant of Chriſt holds forth, with much more to this purpoſe, taking off the grand objection is made againſt it in the ſame Treatiſa, p. 138, 139.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Burroughes</hi> on <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſpeaking againſt wanton Profeſſors in this Age, ſaith, <q>We finde revealed in the Goſpel, that it is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:165014:25"/>God that muſt work the will and the deed; the Covenant of grace is ſuch, as that God doth not onely require, but work all for us. How is this goodneſſe (ſaith he) miſ-interpreted and abuſed? Therefore (ſay they) what need wee doe any thing? Why doe Miniſters urge people to duties? Your principle is good, the truth is good, that it is God that workes all in the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> but this deduction is very abſurd and vile, and an abuſe of Gods goodneſſe, that therefore you muſt not work together with God, as rationall creatures, &amp;c. p 743.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Greenhill,</hi> in his elaborate Lectures on <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> Chap. 3. verſe 1, 2, 3. p. 293. <hi>Obſerv;</hi> 1. hath theſe words, <q>The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muſt act and put forth their graces towards further reception of ſpirituall things; When Chriſt will give <hi>Ezekiel Donum Prophetiae,</hi> a Roll to eat, he opens his mouth, he ſets a-work his faith to receive this gift of propheſie; Faith in the habit is like the mouth ſhut up, nothing enters; but in exerciſe it's like the mouth open, and ready to receive. It's infinite mercy that God at any time will offer us ſpirituall favours and excellencies; we ſhould therefore beforward, and ſtirre up our ſoules and graces to the receit of ſuch mercies. It's a lazy and ill excuſe for godly ones to ſay they can do nothing: Grace is an active &amp;an enabling thing, and where there is a principle of life (as all godly men have) there is a ſpecificall difference between that man and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother that hath it not; a man without it cannot act nor ſtirre up himſelfe to a further reception of ſpirituall things, becauſe he is dead, but a man that hath it, can &amp; ought to quicken up his own ſoule to ſpirituall things. The Prophet had received the Spirit that entred into him, and he opened his mouth, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Faith, to take what the Lord ſhould give: The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> bids <hi>Timothy ſtirre up the gift of God that was in him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. He would have men deal with their gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as they doe with fire vnder the aſhes, they blow them off. and blow the fire up, and there is a flame fit for ſervice. Sloth, feare, infirmity, carnall reaſon, are aſhes that doe oft cover divine fire, that it ſeems dead; but we muſt ſtirre up our ſelves, blow off thoſe aſhes, and blow up the fire of grace, that it may burn and ſhine, be uſefull to our ſelves and others. The Prophet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains in <hi>Eſay</hi> 64.7. <hi>There is no man that ſtirreth up himſelfe to take hold of me:</hi> they are like men aſleep, that ſit ſtill and doe nothing.</q> The vulgar is, <hi>Non eſt qui conſurgat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:165014:25"/>So that I conceive as it is in the great buſineſſe of a Beleevers mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of ſin, ſo it is in the performance of prayer, and other religious duties; the <hi>Rule</hi> by which a true beleever is to walk in the performance of thoſe duties, <hi>is not to ſit ſtill and doe nothing</hi> till hee is wrought upon by the Spirit, but hee is through the ſtrength of grace received, to act his<note n="*" place="margin">They that ſpeake againſt performance of duty, might as well ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of faith &amp; exerciſe of grace: for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is nothing elſe but the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of the ſoule with God, the act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of faith, &amp; exerciſe of grace. <hi>Bolt. ut ſupra.</hi>
               </note> faith on the truth and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of God in <hi>the promiſe,</hi> who hath undertaken to give in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to us, and ability to goe through that worke hee calleth us unto, and requireth at our hands. For the ſame God that calls us to duty, hath promiſed to give in <hi>ſtrength</hi> by his Spirit, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge it; and this faith is to rely on, and make uſe of for its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement in all the workes the Lord calls a beleever to the performance of; not but that faith and all other graces are the Spirits, but becauſe the Spirit doth not act without them in a true beleever. For doubtleſſe ſuch as are truly incorporated into Chriſt, and made one Spirit with the Lord, are not acted as <hi>dead ſtockes,</hi> as if every time and moment of their acting Godward, they received <hi>new life</hi> from the Spirit of Chriſt. And I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, for want of the knowledge of this, it comes to paſſe, that many formall eaſie Profeſſors, take ſuch <hi>liberty</hi> to themſelves to live in the <hi>neglect</hi> of holy duties, becauſe they ſay, they <hi>can doe nothing of themſelves further then the Spirit moves and quickens them,</hi> as if one that is in Chriſt, were altogether without ſpiritul life and motion longer then the Holy Ghoſt falls upon him, as in the firſt act of converſion. From whence it muſt needs follow:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there are no <hi>habits</hi> of grace, nor <hi>inherent</hi> workes of holineſſe wrought in beleevers at their firſt <hi>Converſion</hi> and <hi>Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,</hi> when Chriſt is formed in them, which is <hi>contrary</hi> to the<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 1.16. 2 Cor. 5.17. Epheſ. 2.10. Epheſ. 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>Scripture,</hi> and all found Writers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That whenſoever a beleever is without the motions of the Spirit, as in times of <hi>ſleep, and bodily reſt,</hi> or <hi>times of temptation,</hi> yea <hi>falling</hi> into ſin, as the <hi>beſt</hi> are ſubject to doe <hi>James</hi> 3.2. then he is not to be lookt upon as one in Chriſt, which is as abſurd as unſound.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That all thoſe<note n="c" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.14, 25. 2 Tim. 1.6. Luke 21.26. Epheſ 6.18. Iam. 1.19, 21. Phil. 2.12. 1 Cor. 15. ult.</note> 
               <hi>exhortations</hi> to beleevers, that concern the ſtirring up their grace, their <hi>watchfulneſſe</hi> to the performance of religious duties, their <hi>working</hi> out their ſalvation with feare and trembling, Their giving all diligence to make their calling and election ſure, their <hi>fruitfulneſſe</hi> in good workes, and <hi>abounding</hi> in the work of the Lord, &amp;c. are void and of none effect, making
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:165014:26"/>beleevers under the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and new <hi>Covenant</hi> of grace, to be in no better condition then thoſe that were under the <hi>Law,</hi> &amp; a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of works, who had their duties diſcovered, but had not grace and power given to them to enable them to the diſcharge of them, which is contrary to the <hi>Tenor</hi> of the new Covenant, which all thoſe have a ſhare in, that are in Chriſt, and can ſay in ſome meaſure, as Chriſt their Head did, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 40.7, 8, 9. compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>Heb</hi> 10.7, 8. <hi>I delight to doe thy will, O. my God, yea thy Law is within my heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That there are no juſt <hi>grounds</hi> for Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the Scriptures to<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 26.40. Mark 16.14 Luke 24.45. Mat. 25.26. Heb. 5.11, 12. 1 Cor. 5.2. Rev. 2.4. Rev. 3.15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>charge</hi> home the <hi>guilt of ſinnes of omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and neglect</hi> of prayer, repentance, mortification of ſin, &amp;c. nor the guilt of <hi>careleſneſſe, ſlothfulneſſe, negligence, luke-warmneſſe</hi> in the ſervice of God, upon ſuch as are beleevers, which is <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently done by them,</hi> as we may read in the New Teſtament: for if they can act no longer nor no further then the Holy Ghoſt acts them, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t their firſt converſion, then why ſhould they bee char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with ſuch faults, and commanded to amend, threatned if they doe not, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 2 4, 5. ſeeing God deales not with belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in Chriſt under the Goſpel any longer by a <hi>Covenant of works,</hi> but of <hi>grace,</hi> though the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> bee full of juſtice, and in the hands of him who orders it in righteouſneſſe, whoſe<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 89.32, 33.</note> Scepter is a righteous Scepter, and will correct his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in righteouſneſſe yet ſtill in greateſt love and mercy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides ſecondly I anſwer, Doth not this <hi>ground</hi> upon which people build the neglect of duties, &amp;c. as it is propounded, <hi>expoſe them</hi> to great danger of being acted by<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Boltons Bounds of Chriſtian freedom, p. 199.</hi> where hee ſhewes how Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan may move a perſon to the performance of religious duties many wayes.</note> a Spirit of <hi>Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> For ſuppoſe (they ſtaying till the Spirit move them (as they ſpeak in the former <hi>ground</hi>) to pray, &amp;c.) that the motion to the performance of the duty be <hi>irregular,</hi> and <hi>unſeaſonable,</hi> yea alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>unſuitable</hi> to the calling and condition of the party that is moved to the duty, ſhall they forthwith conclude, that this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is from the Spirit of God? Nay, are they not rather to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that it is from <hi>Satan,</hi> who is a <hi>lying and deceiving</hi> Spirit, whoſe <hi>depths and wiles</hi> are <hi>numerous,</hi> and who knowes how to advantage himſelfe againſt us as well by <hi>ill performing</hi> of duties, as by <hi>Non-performing</hi> them: and is it not the generall opinion and judgement of the godly that are <hi>taught of God,</hi> that one ſpeciall differencing <hi>character</hi> between the motions of the Spirit of God and Satan, is this, that the one moves <hi>orderly, ſeaſonably,</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:165014:26"/>
               <hi>ſuitably</hi> to the word, and a perſons calling and condition, but the other <hi>diſorderly, unſeaſonably,</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> to, or at leaſt without the word. And therefore without queſtion, thoſe that build their performing of duties upon this <hi>ground</hi> onely, may as well (eſpecially if they be not experienced Chriſtians) bee delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Satan as led by the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, to ſay no more; are not the Scriptures altogether ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent herein, and doe not in the leaſt hold forth ſuch a <hi>Rule</hi> as this to beleevers, that none ſhould not enter on the performance of duties, till the Spirit move them: nay, is it not as cleare as the <hi>Sunne at Noon day,</hi> that the Scriptures doe <hi>expreſly</hi> hold forth to the contrary,<note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 21.36. Rom. 12.12. Ephel. 6.18. Col. 4.2. 1 Theſſ. 5.17.</note> enjoyning beleevers to pray <hi>alwayes,</hi> to pray <hi>continually,</hi> to pray <hi>without ceaſing,</hi> to <hi>watch unto prayer,</hi> with ſundry the like expreſſions, not (take heed) as if beleevers were to <hi>doe nothing elſe</hi> but pray and perform religious duties; for then there would be no place left for their <hi>civill employments</hi> in their particular <hi>Callings,</hi> which in their place and order are to be done alſo, but that they ſhould endeavour to <hi>preſerve</hi> in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a holy and ſpirituall <hi>diſpoſition</hi> towards that duty, and all other duties of the like <hi>nature,</hi> that ſo they may be ready upon all occaſions, ordinary and extraordinary, publique and privat, to draw nigh to God in the performance of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But doth not this derogate from the honour of the Spirit?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No more then the working of <hi>particular</hi> &amp; next cauſes do from the <hi>univerſall</hi> cauſe, which ſeldom or never produceth parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular effects without a concurrence of particular cauſes. <hi>e. g.</hi> The <hi>Sunne</hi> is the univerſall cauſe of all the fruitfulneſſe of the Earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Bridge Overflowings of Chriſts ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, p. <hi>31, 32.</hi>
               </note> yet it doth not produce that fruitfulneſſe without the help of man: So here, the Spirit of God is the univerſall cauſe of all the ſpirituall actings of the Saints, yet he doth not ordinarily produce thoſe actings without the concurrence of thoſe gracious habits are wrought in their hearts in their converſion. Nay, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of ſuch particular cauſes with the univerſall cauſe, can be no diſhonour to it, in regard that they doe not act by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves properly, but together with and from the influence and vertue of the univerſall, without which they could doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <hi>John</hi> 15.5.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh <hi>Ground</hi> on which people build their neglect of duties, is this, That <hi>the performance of duties and uſe of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:165014:27"/>is more legall then Evangelicall, looking more to a Covenant of workes then a Covenant of Grace; engendring to bondage, where as the Goſpel gives more grace, and affords more liberty, looking more to beleeving then working.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The whole frame of this Argument is <hi>carnall,</hi> and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours too much of the fleſh, and very much <hi>nnbeſeeming</hi> thoſe that would have the world to look upon them as more then <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily</hi> ſpirituall, and ſuch as have attained to greater <hi>enjoyments</hi> of God then others. My <hi>Reaſon</hi> is this, Becauſe thoſe perſons that enjoy <hi>moſt of God,</hi> and live higheſt in the Spirit, have their hearts <hi>moſt enlarged</hi> and carried out in <hi>communion</hi> with God in <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> and eſpecially that of prayer, ſo that I may truly affirme it, <hi>A man of moſt grace is a man of moſt prayer, but a man of leaſt grace is a man of leaſt prayer.</hi> And wee have a ſingular evidence of it in the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> who was as <hi>Evangelicall</hi> a Chriſtian, and lived as highly in God (I ſuppoſe) as any that now caſt off <hi>Ordinances,</hi> how exceedingly was he given to prayer, how much was he in that duty as well as in other duties; but in this of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er he was more then ordinary, ſo frequent, as if he had leaſure for no other employment, and tooke delight in nothing elſe. And hence it is, that he ſaith oftentimes, that he prayed <hi>without</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 1.9. Col. 1.3.9. 2 Tim. 1.3. Phil. 1.4. Philem. v. 4. 2 Theſſ. 1.11. 1 Theſſ. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> that he prayed <hi>alwayes,</hi> that he prayed exceedingly <hi>night and day,</hi> with divers! ſuch like expreſſions. And as it was with this pretious ſervant of Chriſt, ſo it hath been with the moſt <hi>eminentſt beleevers</hi> in all Ages, ſo far have they been from looking on per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of holy Duties, as Legall Services, and <hi>engendring to Bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, if wee diligently obſerve the <hi>Tenor</hi> of the Goſpel, and <hi>new Covenant of Grace,</hi> ſhall we not finde that they call upon beleevers for the <hi>ſtricteſt</hi> and moſt exacteſt <hi>performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ees</hi> of the duties of Gods worſhip, not allowing beleevers to live in the willing neglect of any known duty towards God, or man, or themſelves; if wee are not convinced of it, let that notable place of <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13, 14. be conſidered, where the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſhewes, that the <hi>Grace of God that bringeth ſalvation,</hi> viz. <hi>the Miniſtery of the Goſpel and new Covenant,</hi> that worketh grace <hi>inſtrumentally</hi> in mens hearts, and revealeth the freelove of God through Jeſus Chriſt, to ſinners, hath appeared to all men, teaching us, that <hi>denying ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world:</hi> i. e. ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:165014:27"/>in reſpect of our ſelves, righteouſly or juſtly in reſpect of men, and godly or holily and religiouſly in reſpect of God. In which words I conceive are wrapt up the whole duty of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian as it reſpects the firſt and ſecond Table. This is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel, or new Covenant of grace, not of the Law, or Covenant of workes: And the Apoſtle in the 14. verſe goes on to amplifie it, by ſhewing one chiefe end of Chriſts comming into the world was, to redeem them from iniquity, and to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to himſelfe a people zealous of good workes; where he gives us alſo a character of thoſe that are the peculiar redeemed ones of Chriſt, that they are ſuch as are not onely freed from the power and thraldome of their luſts, but are made zealous of good works. To this place many more might be added, as <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74 75. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.14 &amp; 6.27.37.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, it's conſiderable to examine and enquire what this <hi>Liberty</hi> is which the Goſpel brings with it to beleevets; now without queſtion it cannot be meant of a <hi>lawleſſe liberty,</hi> a <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, ſenſuall, ſinfull liberty, a liberty and freedome</hi> to diſhonour Chriſt, to caſt his Lawes and Ordinances behind <hi>our backes,</hi> and to live as we liſt. It's as cleare as the Sunne at noon day, that the <hi>Goſpel</hi> brings no ſuch liberty with it to the world: indeed the <hi>Devils Goſpel</hi> doth, and <hi>Antichriſts,</hi> and <hi>Mahumets,</hi> they give to people elbow-roome enough, as we uſe to ſay, in the wayes of ſinne, but not ſo with the <hi>glorious Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.14. Rom. 6 14. 2 Tim. 2.19. 1 Ioh. 3.3. Rom. 6.1, 2.</note> for this ſaith, Chriſt came to redeem us <hi>from</hi> iniquity, this ſayth, ſin ſhall have <hi>no Dominion</hi> over us, this ſaith, whoſoever names the Name of Chriſt, muſt depart from iniquity, this ſaith, hee that hath true hope in Chriſt, <hi>purifies</hi> himſelfe as Chriſt is pure; this ſaith, we are not to <hi>continue</hi> in ſinne that grace may abound, nay it demands a reaſon how men can imagine that thoſe that are dead to ſinne (through intereſt in Chriſt) ſhould live any longer therein;<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.14, 15. 1 Cor: 15. ult. Phil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11. Tit 3.8. 2 Cor. 7.1. Phil 3.13, 14.</note> and doth not the Goſpel of Chriſt ſay alſo, that wee ſhould be holy as Chriſt is holy, that we ſhould <hi>abound</hi> in the work of the Lord, that we ſhould be <hi>filled</hi> with all the fruits of <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> that we ſhould bee <hi>zealous of good works,</hi> and maintain good workes, and perfect <hi>holines</hi> in the feare of the Lord, forgetting what is behinde, and preſſing after what is before, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Beſides fourthly, the uſe of <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and performance of duties under the Goſpel, is to bee lookt upon as a <hi>Beleevers
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:165014:28"/>priviledge,</hi> not as his <hi>burthen:</hi> and if the commands and ſervice of Chriſt be called a <hi>Yoke and a Burthen,</hi> and <hi>Bonds</hi> and <hi>Cords,</hi> in the judgement of men, yet it's an <hi>eaſie</hi> yoke, and a <hi>light</hi> bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, ſuch <hi>cords and bonds</hi> as are gentle, ſo that as the Apoſtle ſaith, his commandements are not <hi>grievous,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5 3. The pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagogy of <hi>Moſes</hi> indeed was <hi>burdenſome</hi> and grievous, ſo that our fore-fathers could not beare it; but not ſo with the ſervice of Chriſt under the Goſpel, when heavenly and ſpirituall ſoules are in it. Indeed when carnall hearts enter upon, or tarry any time <hi>in and under</hi> the ſervice of Chriſt, they are as under a burthen, and the worke they are about is a burthen to them; and what's the reaſon but this, that there is an <hi>unſuitableneſſe</hi> between the work and their hearts, neither come they to enjoy communion with Chriſt in <hi>Duty,</hi> but come to <hi>the very duty</hi> as men do to their <hi>task</hi> or daily labour:<note place="margin">Vide Bolt. true Bounds of Chriſtians Freedom, p. 213, 214.</note> now that perſon that hath to doe with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but duty in duty, cannot chuſe but finde that duty <hi>tedious</hi> and irkſome to him, as the ordinances under the <hi>Law</hi> were to the <hi>carnall Jewes</hi> that did not eye Chriſt in them. But now on the other ſide, when a gracious <hi>ſpirituall</hi> heart comes to a ſpirituall duty, &amp; not to the duty ſo much as to God and Chriſt in the duty, to converſe with the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Sonne</hi> in the Spirit, how <hi>ſweet</hi> and <hi>delightfull</hi> then are times of duty unto ſuch ſoules, ſo that the performance of duties in a right manner, is no <hi>Legall</hi> thing, nor matter of burthen and griefe to the Saints; but that which affords them the greateſt ſweetneſſe, content and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is to be enjoyed on this ſide glory, and ſo is to bee lookt on as matter of <hi>priviledge,</hi> not of <hi>bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. To ſay no more; whereas it is ſaid, that the <hi>Goſpel requires be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving,</hi> not working; if by <hi>working</hi> you underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the purchaſing of life and ſalvation at the hands of God by our performances, the juſtification of a ſinner before God, &amp;c. it's granted, the Goſpel requires it not at the hands of ſinners, becauſe it offers <hi>more grace,</hi> that is, it ſhewes us the <hi>work is done</hi> to our hands by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, he hath procured our ranſome, ſatisfied his Fathers Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, appeaſed his wrath, procured peace and reconciliation, and that firmly through his own blood, and wrought all our workes for us <hi>this way, Eſay</hi> 26.12. And our duty is primarily, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, to <hi>beleeve this,</hi> and accept this as it is held forth in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Iohn 6.29. 1 Iohn 3.23.</note> becauſe the great work of God, and commandement of the Goſpel, is to <hi>beleeve</hi> in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, that we
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:165014:28"/>may be ſaved. But if by <hi>working</hi> wee underſtand the fruit that flowes from our beleeving in Chriſt, and taking hold of him to juſtification and ſalvation, <hi>viz.</hi> a holy <hi>ſtudy in all our wayes to pleaſe God, and doe his will, to walk in a childlike fear and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence before God, and have reſpect to all his commandements, that in all things we may be found to the honour and praiſe of him that hath loved us, and called us out of darkneſſe into his marvellous light, &amp;c.</hi> then I ſuppoſe there is none whatſoever that pretends to Chriſtianity (eſpecially if he have in an experimentall manner felt the love of Chriſt <hi>ſhed abroad</hi> in his heart) but will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Goſpel requires ſuch <hi>working.</hi> And the whole ſcope of the New Teſtament is ſo cleare and plain for this, as that none but ſuch to whom the Goſpel is <hi>hid,</hi> can be ignorant of it. If any deſire further ſatisfaction herein, (for it would be too large for me to produce all that might be ſpoken to this particular) let him read thoſe Goſpel<note n="*" place="margin">Downam <hi>of Iuſtification,</hi> l. 7. c. 1. p. 434, 435, 436, 437, 438. Biſco's <hi>golri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous myſtery of Gods mercy, p.</hi> 298, 299. Eatons <hi>Hony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb.</hi> Boltons <hi>bounds of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians freedom.</hi> Burges <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciae legis, p.</hi> 39, 40, 41, 42, 43. <hi>with many other. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Treatiſes</hi> that are abroad concerning this poynt.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Another ground upon which people build their caſting off the uſe of Word and Ordinances, is this, Becauſe the Word and Ordinances are nothing without the Spirit. They can never work any impreſſion upon the ſoule, or acquaint the Spirit of a man or woman, that the Lord is his God, or that Chriſt is his Saviour, &amp;c. but this belongs to the office of the Spirit of God; the Word and Ordinances of themſelves are never able to work ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in the ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I find an anſwer to this objection in Doctor <hi>Criſp, vol.</hi> 3. p. 93. 94. 95. which becauſe his workes have been of great eſteeme amongſt ſuch people not long ſince, and becauſe he ſpeakes fully to the point in hand, I will here tranſcribe, as they are in the book ſet downe; the words are theſe, <hi>p.</hi> 94. What ſerve all the Ordinances for, will you ſay? Is not here a crying down of Ordinances? There will be ſtill this ſcandall caſt upon us: But let me tell you, there is a moſt comfortable uſe of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, though they ſerve not to ſuch high purpoſes as theſe are: I ſay, though they are not efficient to beget, and finde out, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale to the ſpirits of men the things that concern God, yet <hi>beſide the efficient revelation of God</hi> to be out God from the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit alone,</hi> there is a <hi>paſſive Inſtrument,</hi> by which the Lord doth make himſelfe known to be the God of his people, but that way is meerly paſſive, not active.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:165014:29"/>1. Paſſively God makes himſelfe known to be the God of his people by the word of his grace, and faith laying hold on the word of grace revealed, and more <hi>ſubordinately</hi> in <hi>prayer, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, receiving the Lords, Supper,</hi> and ſuch ordinances, ſo farre as they are mixed with faith. Now give me leave to communicate to you the full uſe and utmoſt extent of Gods thoughts concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ordinances that he hath propounded, how farre forth he would have the creature look upon the ordinances, and as much as may be put upon the uſe of them, ſo farre forth as they are uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Know therefore, as I ſaid before, that all theſe ordinances are but paſſive wayes of conveying this great gift, the knowledge of God to be our God, I mean more plainly thus: Theſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances are onely of, and in themſelves, empty, dry Channels, or Pipes, through which the Spirit of the Lord brings from God himſelfe the Spring, thoſe riches, and conveyes the ſame into the Spirit of a man. Look as a channell digged in a dry ground, is the way through which the Spring conveyes his water unto a ciſtern, the channell it ſelfe communicates none of its own, onely it is a paſſage through which the Spring conveyes his water: So are all the ordinances, even faith it ſelfe, prayer, and all other Services, they are but channels through which the Spirit of the Lord paſſeth and bringeth from the Lord himſelfe (the Spring and Fountaine) the revelation of God to be our God. In all the reſt of the gifts of God, which he hath ſo freely beſtowed, never a gift of Gods Spirit procures any thing of its own, our faith hath nothing of its own, faſting and prayer have nothing of their own, but as the Lord hath been pleaſed to make theſe ordinances to bee paſſages to convey himſelfe to the ſonnes of men, and ſo they are to bee made uſe of by the ſonnes of men: Faith as it apprehendeth the Lord Jeſus, and other Ordinances, as therein true faith is exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and no otherwiſe. And indeed beloved, this is the loadſtone to provoke perſons to the uſe of all ordinances, God hath ranked them together, that the Lord hath ſo much and ſo often promiſed through them, to convey himſelfe. <hi>You are kept through the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God through faith</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>unto ſalvation.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, The Lord doth convey himſelfe, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of his own ſalvation through our beleeving. The Spirit of the Lord paſſing <hi>through the Miniſtery of the Goſpel,</hi> as the breath of man paſſeth through a Trumpet; the Trumpet is the inſtrument, the breath is the Spirit of the Lord: the Trumpet
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:165014:29"/>adds nothing to the breath. Now know beloved, ſo far as you wil attend the Ordinances, <hi>becauſe God calls out to Ordinances,</hi> and becauſe you have heard the Lord to promiſe to beſtow ſuch things upon you in the ordinances, ſo farre you ſhall attend the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances according to his pleaſure; but when you aſcend ſo high, that the ordinance doth get things, then you rob the Lord, and give more to ordinances then God hath given. <q>Now though the ordinances have no efficiency of their own, in the nature I have ſpoken, yet there is good cauſe for all Gods own people to eſteem very highly of ordinances, and to be joyfull of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and to long much after ordinances, to make much of them, for why the Lord hath made his <hi>promiſes to be found</hi> of them, &amp; to be <hi>with them</hi> in ordinances. In the day of adverſitie call thou upon me and I will deliver thee. And here by the way know from hence what is the expectation of beleevers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which they ought to have of the Lord for ſuch things, when they come to ſuch ordinances, that ſo, when we attend the Lord in his ordinances, we may find him in them, &amp;c. Therefore as the poore man lay at the Beautifull Gate, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Gate would relieve him, but becauſe it was a place of concourſe where honorable men reſorted, from whom he might have Almes; ſo in the Miniſtery, in faſting and prayer, and all other ſervices, there is the gate of the Temple of the Lord, there is the place the Lord makes uſually his concourſe and reſort, there is the place God appoints to give the meeting; therefore in expectation of the Word of his grace, that we may find him in <hi>Ordinances,</hi> we doe reſort to them.</q> Now what derogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is there all this while from the <hi>Ordinances,</hi> while we make the but thus paſſive? The richeſt treaſure in the world may come to a man through the pooreſt veſſell; the treaſure is never the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther off, nor never the worſe, becauſe the veſſell is poore. It is no matter of what price the meanes of conveyance is, ſo that the thing we deſire be conveyed to us by it, onely we muſt not give it that which is above its due, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And this ſhal be encouragement ſufficient to wait upon all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of all ſorts, where the Lord appoints, that he will for his owne ſake give you a gracious anſwer, and <hi>beſtow all good things upon you that you ſtand in need of, in ordinances,</hi> This is motive ſufficient, I ſay, to ſtirre you up to attend upon ordinances, and yet not to make Gods of them, to aſcribe that to them which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:165014:30"/>alone to God <hi>(who doth all ordinarily through ordinances)</hi> which is the only way to diſappoint you of your hope, when you expect help from them.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The 9. ground upon which people build their caſting off the uſe of Ordinances, is the ſeverall Texts of Scripture which ſeem to plead for the <hi>Non-performance of duties, and laying aſide of all ordinances in the ties of the Goſpel;</hi> As,</p>
            <q>They ſhall not teach every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, ſaying, Know the Lord: For all ſhall know me from the leaſt to the greateſt. <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 8.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>We have alſo a more ſure word of Propheſie, whereunto yee doe well that yee take heed, as unto a light that ſhineth in a dark place, untill the day dawn, and the Day-ſtarre ariſe in your hearts. <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Pet. 1.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>But the anointing which yee have received of him, abideth in you: and yee need not that any man teach you: but as the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing teacheth you of all things, and is truth, and is no lie: and even as it hath taught you, ye ſhall abide in him, <bibl>
                  <hi>1 John 2.27.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>And I ſaw no Temple therein; for the Lord God Almighty, and the Lamb are the Temple of it, <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 21, 22.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>And the Citie had no need of the Sunne, neither of the Moon to ſhine in it: for the glory of God did lighten it, and the Lamb is the light thereof. <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſ. 23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Much might be ſpoken in anſwer to ſuch as produce theſe and the like Scriptures for the <hi>ceſſation of Goſpel-ordinances;</hi> but I ſhall ſtudy brevity, and referre all to two heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Show what I conceive to be the proper meaning of theſe texts of Scripture.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Give in the joynt conſent of the moſt judicious and godly Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors with it, that have written on theſe Scriptures.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Touching the firſt, I ſuppoſe that the holy Ghoſt in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Scriptures, doth not in the leaſt, mean or intend, that the Word, Ordinances, and Miniſtery, appointed and inſtituted by Jeſus Chriſt in the dayes of the New Teſtament for the Saints to make uſe of, ſhould be laid aſide, and not at all made uſe of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have ſhewed in my <hi>Quaeries,</hi> that in the <hi>pureſt</hi> Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, Chriſt will have Ordinances, and Officers to adminiſter them, and Saints to enjoy them, though in a purer manner then they have been, or poſſibly now are; but I conceive he meanes, that Chriſt himſelfe will be their <hi>Teacher</hi> in the new ſtate of his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:165014:30"/>Church, in the uſe of theſe his own meanes he hath inſtitured and appointed. And this teaching of Chriſt, the King and Head of his Church, will be, I conceive, divers wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By giving the Saints a greater meaſure of the Spirit, and a more nearer communion and fellowſhip with himſelfe then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, the fulneſſe of God ſhall be more brought into their hearts by the miniſtery of the Spirit; and then Chriſt ſhall be all in all indeed: not <hi>all without all,</hi> but <hi>all in all,</hi> that is, <hi>all in all Saints,</hi> and <hi>all in all Ordinances,</hi> and <hi>all in all duties,</hi> and <hi>all in all mercies;</hi> ſo that nothing ſhal be lifted up, acknowledged and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but Chriſt alone, and the Father in him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By making the Saints to be ſo wiſe and underſtanding to ſalvation, that they ſhall not <hi>hang or pin</hi> their faith upon the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of men, the <hi>Authority of Parliaments, Councels, Synods, Conventions, Dictates, Decrees, Iudgements</hi> of men, though never ſo <hi>wiſe, learned godly,</hi> but they ſhall cleave to the <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Scriptures</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and reſt upon the <hi>teachings</hi> of the Spirit in the Word, who is alone the infallible teacher and revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the mind of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By clearing tho truth made known by outward inſtruments, after ſo ſure a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tain a manner by the Spirit inwardly, that the outward teaching ſhall be as no teaching in compariſon of the inward operation and concurrence of the holy Ghoſt perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them, as the <hi>Samaritans</hi> when they came to Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe upon the report of the woman that had been with him, they got ſuch ſatisfaction from him, that they ſaid, <hi>Now we beleeve, not becauſe of thy ſaying, for we have heard him our ſelves, and know that this is indeed that Chriſt,</hi> Joh 4.42. Even thus doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, will the Lord Jeſus deale with the Saints when thoſe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious times come, he will by his Spirit inwardly ſo make known the myſtery of the Goſpel preached outwardly, that they ſhall ſay to thoſe that are his inſtruments, Now we beleeve and underſtand, not ſo much becauſe of your ſaying, as that we have heard him ourſelves teaching us inwardly by his Spirit. This I take to be the ſcope and ſenſe of thoſe Texts of Scriptures, not a taking away the uſe of ordinances, but a more ſpirituall and fuller enjoyment of God and Jeſus Chriſt in them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Touching the judgement of the godly agreeing with me herein, take a few in ſtead of many that might be alledged.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Pareus,</hi> that famous and judicious. Writer, in his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:165014:31"/>on <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.11. hath theſe words: <hi>Non itaque hinc recta conficiunt fanatici, miniſterio Eccleſiae opus non eſſe in novo Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamento, quo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am ad complement um tanta luck Deus in huc vitae per miniſterium Evangelii nos preparat. Fides enim eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, auditus per verbum Dei; Ideo dedit Chriſtrs alios Apoſtolos, alios Doctores, ut Eccleſia exedificetur ad perfectionem futioram. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trumque docet Scriptura, omnes docert à Deo, &amp; omnes debere audire, legere, meditare ſcriptur as &amp; verbum Dei. Itaque pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſiones non evertunt praecepta; neque poſitae cauſa prima tollun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur mediae. Ut enim non ſequitur, Deus omnes paſcit, ergo non opus eſt pane &amp; agricultura, per haec enim media Deus paſcit. Ita non ſequitur Deus omnes docet, ergo non opus eſt verbe. Per verbum enim auditum &amp; praedicaetum omnes doret.</hi> The interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is this; Therefore thoſe brain-ſick men doe not rightly ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that there is no need of the miniſtry to the Church in the times of the new Teſtament, becauſe God to the compleating of ſo great light in this life, doth prepare us by the Miniſtery of the Goſpel; for faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. Therefore Chriſt gave ſome to be Apoſtles, others to be Teachers, that the Church might be built up to future per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. And the Scripture doth teach both, <hi>viz.</hi> all to be taught of God, and all ought to heare, read, meditate on the Scriptures and word of God. Therefore the promiſes doe not overthrow the commands and precepts, nor the firſt prime cauſe take away the meanes: For as it doth not follow, that becauſe God feedeth us, therefore there is no need of bread nor husbandry, or tilling and ſowing the earth; for by theſe very meanes God feedeth us; ſo it doth not follow, becauſe God reacheth all, therefore there is no need of the Word: for by the Word heard and preached he teacheth all.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee by a little, how the judgement of this famous Writer joynes with us in what was formerly delivered touching the true and genuine ſenſe of thoſe Scriptures; he hath much more in the ſame place upon his ſolution of divers queſtions to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>So learned <hi>Hyperius</hi> in his Commentary on this place of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> is ſo full and copious, that I hardly know any have written more largely on this ſubject (unleſſe it hath been in a Treatiſe by it ſelfe) anſwering all objections againſt it, which would be too much to tranſcribe in this place.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:165014:31"/>2. For that place of 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. many of the Ancients have underſtood it of the ſtate of glory: but learned <hi>Gerard</hi> in his Expoſition of the words, ſhewes it to be underſtood of Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times here. <hi>Sed per diem illuceſcentem &amp; Phoſphorum orientem rectiùs intelligitur uberior, perfectior, clarior, &amp; magis expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata Chriſti &amp; myſteriorum divinorum cognitio.</hi> And this hee proves by five Arguments, but yet reproves thoſe that would hereby lay aſide the Scriptures, and look upon them as unuſefull to them, when the Day-ſtarre is riſen in their hearts; conſidering the whole ſtate of the New Teſtament-light, is no other to that of glory, then the midnight is to the noon-day; and eſpecially becauſe that the dawning of the day, and the ariſing of the Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarre in our hearts, ſpoken of here, is meant of the Miniſtery and Doctrine of the Apoſtles, who were the beſt interpreters of the Prophets, Chriſt himſelfe having (before his aſcenſion) opened their underſtandings to that end, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.44, 45. <hi>Sic ergo ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monem Propheticum comparat Apoſtólus lucernae tempore noctis lucenti; Apoſtolicum vero ſermonem, ſeu Evangelii in N. T. praedicationem comparat Lucifero &amp; diei plenam lucem adferenti, &amp; hac ratione majorem doctrinae claritatem N. T. tribuit.</hi> And thus <hi>Piſcator, Beza,</hi> and others underſtand the place; ſo that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers are to have reſpect to the Scriptures alwayes, both of the old and new Teſtament, and not to caſt off the uſe of them, as ſoon as the <hi>Day-ſtarre</hi> begins to riſe in their hearts, that is, ſo ſoon as they come to underſtand or attaine a more cleare know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the doctrine of the Goſpel, or ſalvation by faith alone in Chriſt crucified, by the miniſtery and teaching of the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Concerning that Text of 1 <hi>John</hi> 2 27. in my judgement <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> ſpeake out the proper ſenſe of the place,<note place="margin">Vide Bee. Annot. Calv. in loc.</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That the Apoſtle in theſe words, onely ſignifieth to thoſe he wrote, that <hi>they were not ſo ignorant as to be taught ſuch things as were unknown to them, or that hee propounded ſuch things to them, as the Spirit of Chriſt which they had received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hearts, did not readily prompt and make known unto them.</hi> And therefore faith <hi>Calvin, Frantick men doe raſhly from hence ſeek to ſhut out of the Church the uſe of the publique Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery.</hi> For in that the Apoſtle ſaith, that they are taught in all things by the Spirit, it muſt not be generally taken, but reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the circumſtance of the preſent place, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As for that of <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.22, 23. though the moſt (both
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:165014:32"/>Ancient and Modern) Writers, doe underſtand it of the Church Triumphant hereafter in glory; yet M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Brightman</hi> and others, take it to be meant of the glorious times of the Church here on earth, when the Jewes ſhall be called, and come to their full glory in Goſpel-enjoyments. At which time the worſhip that ſhall then be in uſe, ſhall be moſt ſimple, and moſt pure, &amp;c. <hi>Let the Jewes</hi> (therefore ſaith he) <hi>hearken to this, and let them not expect the re-edifying of a new materiall Temple amongst them any longer, as they have done to this day fooliſhly and perverſty, but let them breathe and bray with their hearts &amp; hearty wiſhes ter the right manner of worſhipping God, which ſhall not ſtand in need of any Temple: Let them long with hopefull hearts to ſee Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God himſelfe, and the Lamb converſing among them; in reſpect of which glory, they ſhall judge whatſoever can be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the policie of men, are but vile and nothing worth.</hi> And then afterward upon the 23. verſe. <hi>Now theſe things</hi> (ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Brightman) <hi>are not ſpoken to this purpoſe, as if there ſhould be no uſe at all of the Scriptures, but becauſe all men ſhall be ſo able to underſtand the will of God at this time, as if they had no need to be brought to knowledge by the reading and ſtudying of the Scriptures, or any other holy bookes which help to open them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this agree M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> on the <hi>Revelations,</hi> with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes</hi> on <hi>Hoſea,</hi> and divers other late Writers.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Laſtly, though ſome of thoſe that renounce Ordinances, will make uſe of Scriptures, ſo farre as they conceive will advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage their cauſe, (as is the property of all Heretickes to doe) yet for the moſt part ſuch perſons wholly renounce them, calling it a dead letter, a common writing, of no more value, truth and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, then the writings and ſayings of other Saints, containing in them many weake, ſilly, vain, groſſe, and contrary things, and therefore not to be made uſe of, eſpecially by grown Chriſtians, as a Rule to guide them; but the Saints are to follow the dictates and teachings of the Spirit within them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It ſeemes then that the Scriptures, or the word of God which was written by the holy Prophets and Apoſtles, (who were infallibly led and guided by the holy Ghoſt in the penning of the Old and New Teſtament, as I ſhall ſhew in the following Anſwers) will ſerve young Chriſtians turnes, and may bea help to ſuch as are poore, weake, low beleevers, Babes in Chriſt. Well then, they are ſome way uſefull: but why not as
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:165014:32"/>uſefull and ſerviceable to<note n="*" place="margin">S. Seripturae uſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſui et neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitatem non ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion rudibus &amp; Alphabetarils in Chriſtianiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, ſed &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectioribus ac regenitis paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim commendat, nec tantum in vetere, ſed eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am in novo Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamento quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum ex multis Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae locis &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplis liquet. <hi>Synopſ. pur. Theolog.</hi>
               </note> old men in Chriſt, to ſtrong and well grown Chriſtians, as to them that are weak? Nay, is it not evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that not onely the moſt eminenteſt Saints before Chriſt came into the world, as <hi>David, Daniel, &amp;c.</hi> but after Chriſt was come, made uſe of the Scriptures, as their rule and guide in knowing and doing the mind and will of God. Let us make a tryall.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Apoſtles, though they had ſuch a fulneſſe of the Spirit powred out upon them, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. yet they made uſe of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Peter</hi> did, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10, 11, 12. and chap. 2.6. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1, 20, 21. and chap. 3.16. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who was caught up into the third heaven, (whoſe divine enjoyments were ſo great, that few could match him) he made uſe of the Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.2.4.3.9.17.10.11.11.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8, 22.4 30. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3, 4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.18. So the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> he made uſe of them, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.8, 23, 4.5. So the Evangeliſts, we read how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten they quoted the Scriptures. So <hi>Apollos</hi> was mighty in the Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> 18 24.28. So the <hi>Bereans,</hi> they ſearched daily the Scriptures, and were highly commended for it, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. Yea, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe, (our alone bleſſed Saviour) made uſe of the Scriptures often, as we finde <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.38. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. <hi>Luke</hi> 20.37. <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.42.22.29. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.27, 32, 45. Neither did Chriſt and his Apoſtles make uſe onely of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for their own uſe, but charged others to make uſe of the Scriptures, and thoſe alſo that were no mean Chriſtians, but ſuch as had attained a great meaſure of the Spirit. That they gave the Saints in charge to make uſe of the Scriptures, is evident from <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.39. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.3, 4. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.14, 15, 16, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</p>
            <p>That they were no mean, but well grown Saints, and ſuch as had attained to a great meaſure of the Spirit, is alſo evident from the Epithites the Apoſtles give them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. For firſt, they ſtile them ſuch, whoſe faith is ſpoken of throughout the whole world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>2. Such as were wiſe men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.15. I ſpeak <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>ſapientibus,</hi> to wiſe men.</item>
               <item>3. Such as were perfect, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Let us therefore as many as be perfect,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>4. Such as had received <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. e. <hi>Like pretious faith.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1.</item>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:165014:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:165014:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <item>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:165014:34"/>5. Such as were ſtrong men in Chriſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2 14.</item>
               <item>6. Such whoſe faith did grow exceedingly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 13.</item>
            </list>
            <p>So that by all this it plainly appeares, that the Scriptures are uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to all the Saints, high as well as low, ſtrong as well as weake, wife as wel as ſimple, yea every way able to furniſh <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the man of God himſelfe, or inſtruct him perfectly, as the word<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſignifies. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17. to every good worke; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it's a fond and idle thing in any to ſay, that any of the Saints, while they are here <hi>in via,</hi> are above the uſe of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas they ſay, the Scriptures are not to be a Rule for the Saints to walk by, in matters of faith &amp; practice, becauſe they are a dead letter, common writings, containing in them many weak, filly, yea groſſe contradictions, &amp;c. I anſwer, This is blaſphemy againſt the holy Ghoſt, (that was the Author of them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21.) in a high degree: For it's as cleare as the Sunne, to any but thoſe whoſe eyes are ſhut up, that the Scriptures are without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, without weakneſſe, vanity or<note n="b" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Roberts</hi> Keye of the Bible, p. 38. to 49. excellently clearing and freeing the Scriptures fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contradictions in themſelves.</note> contrariety, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by him who is Perfection it ſelfe, 2 <hi>Tom.</hi> 3.16. Now if they be inſpired of God; then they muſt needs be the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of all other writings, both for <hi>verity, purity, certainty, efficacy, perfection</hi> &amp; <hi>perpetuity,</hi> as were eaſie to<note n="c" place="margin">Read Maſter <hi>Traps</hi> Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia Theologiae, <hi>or</hi> the true Treaſury.</note> demonſtrate, which made one to call the Scriptures, <hi>Liber Librorum,</hi> the Book of Books; in compariſon of which all other are but<note n="d" place="margin">Sibyllae folia, Luciani libri, imò ipſae Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopi Fabulae, vanitas vanita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> leaves, fables, trifles, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of vanities, &amp;c. which drew this ſaying from<note n="e" place="margin">Auferantur de medio char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae noſtrae, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedat in mediu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> codex Dei. <hi>In Pſal. 57.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtine</hi> of old, Away with our writings, that room may be made for the book of God: and that of renowned<note n="f" place="margin">Ego odi me è libros, &amp; ſaepe opto eos interire &amp;c. <hi>In Gen.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Luther,</hi> I heartily hate mine own bookes, and could wiſh them out of the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I feare they keep men from ſpending ſo much time from rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Gods book, the onely fountain of all the wiſdome. Now if the Scriptures are ſo excellent, ſo perfect,, why ſhould they not then ſerve to us as a Cauon or rule to walk by, in things that are both to be beleeved and practiſed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But they are a dead letter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And why ſo? Are the words of the<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>We muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver abſtract the Scripture from that Spirit of God which is alwayes in it, and with it, as a clear and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, and as the very life and ſoul of it; whereas you with the Papiſts take the Scripture for no other but as a bare letter, or bark of a tree, or dead corps without any divine ſpirit in it.</hi> Mr. <hi>Burious</hi> Reply to a Relation of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the laſt Archbiſhop of <hi>Cant.</hi> and <hi>Fiſher</hi> the Ieſuite. For even as the veines in a natural body, do carry and convey in them the life blood; and as the arteries do contain in them thoſe animall ſpirits conveyed from the head to all the members, whereby they are vegetated and moved: ſo the Scriptures, and every part of them have in them the Spirit whereby they are quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and which is in them, as the light in the body of the Sun, their proper light, &amp;c. p. 151.</note> living God dead
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:165014:34"/>words? Are they not ſpirit and life? <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.63. Are they not quick and powerfull, ſharper then a two-edged Sword, piercing even to the dividing aſunder of Soule and Spirit, and of the joynts and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intentions of the heart, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.12. How are they then a dead letter?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But they are full of contradictions, leaving men ſtill in the dark, and under uncertainties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If we apprehend any darkneſſe or contradictions in the Scriptures, the fault is ours, and not theirs, 'tis <hi>defectus vaſis, non fontis:</hi> There is a ſufficiency of light that accompanies and ſhines forth in the Scriptures continually; but that we cannot ſee it, is becauſe we come to it with blind eyes, <hi>Not habemus non limpidos, ſed lippos oculos,</hi> as <hi>Aquinas</hi> notes on <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.3. There are unſearchable treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge in the Scriptures, as there is light in the Sunne beaming forth to the world; but that men cannot diſcerne it, is from their own dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and not the Scriptures. How mach the blinde Papiſts have urged the obſeurity of the Scriptures againſt our Writers (the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to keep up Antichriſt on his throne by keeping the vulgar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in ignorance, through prohibiting and forbidding them to read the Scriptures) and how abundantly they have been confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is<note n="h" place="margin">It is true, the Scriptures are obſcure and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, but not all, nor to all, nor alwayes. <hi>1.</hi> All the Scriptures are not difficult and obſcure, every part of them is not invol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d in obſcunity, <hi>2 Pet. 3.16.</hi> theſe things thas areneceſſary to ſalvation, are plainly ſet down. <hi>2.</hi> Thoſe places in the Scripture that are obſcure, are not ſo to all perſons, but as the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, they are ſo to the unlearned and unſtable, that is, to them that are meere Naturals, or Animals, <hi>1 Cor. 2.14.</hi> Such as want the aſſiſtance of the Spirit to give them underſtanding. <hi>3.</hi> Neither are they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure alwayes: For thoſe that are dark to day, and cannot underſtand the mind of God, may have it revealed and made known to them to morrow. <hi>Vide Langfords Enquiry after verity.</hi>
               </note> plain to thoſe that have any acquaintance with their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverfies. Admirable things have been done in this Age this way, both in <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſo that people are left without excuſe herein.</p>
            <p>And as for contradictions in the Scriptures, it is from the ſame ſpirit of falſhood that acts and workes in men to ſpeak ſo diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully as they do of them. For how can the moſt High, who is the Author of the Scriptures, and in whom is no darknes at all, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.5. be the God of truth and falſhood together; and it, muſt of nececeſſity follow, if the Scriptures ſpeak plain contradictions that either <hi>Jehovah</hi> could not, or that he would not ſpeake ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:165014:35"/>as to have his minde knowne by his creatures, though he call upon them to look after it, which is blaſphemy in a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. It were to be wiſhed that Chriſtians would come to the Scriptures with leſſe<note n="i" place="margin">Cum corde noſtro nos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordemus: Et Scriptura ſancta an nulla parte diſcordat. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> diſcord in their own hearts, and a greater ſenſe of their own perſonall darkneſſe, weakneſſe and infirmity, that they may crave the divine aſſiſtance of Chriſt, to open their underſtandings, and take more paines to find out the mind of God by comparing one text with another, thoſe that are more obſcure with thoſe that are cleare, and weigh circumſtances, <hi>Anteceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia &amp; Conſequentia.</hi> i. e. what goes before, and what followes after the text, which would very much help them to know what the mind of God is in it, and not preſently fall<note n="k" place="margin">Deus bone! in veritds ipſa quae eſt Author Scripturae, an ſpiritus ſanctus à quo acti fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ſancti Dei illi homines lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes &amp; ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentes, anſacra ſcriptura tota divinitus inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata ſibi contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicere poteſt. Tum enim Deus cjuſque ſpiritus ſimul veritatis &amp; mendacii ſpiritus eſſet, et divinae hujus veritatis pars une neceſſariò vera, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>era neceſſariò falſa eſſet, cum coniradicentium unum ueceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riò vervm alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum falſum ſit. <hi>Vid. Sharph. Symphon. in Epiſt.</hi>
               </note> foule on the Scriptures themſelves, as affirming and denying one and the ſame thing. But this is the miſery of this age, that as <hi>Auſtine</hi> once ſpake of the <hi>Manichees,</hi> ſo may I of people now, that they wil not ſubject their opinions and judgements to the Scriptures, but would ſubject the Scriptures to their opinions. Such places as have but the leaſt outward appearance or ſhew to make for them, thoſe they will cleave firmly to, but ſuch as directly ſpeak againſt them, they throw away and cry out of contradictions, when the difference all the while is in themſelves, and not in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, whereas they ſay the Saints are to follow the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and ſecret Dictates and Teachings of the Spirit within them, and conforme to them as the onely guide and <hi>Cynoſura</hi> of all they beleeve and practiſe, and therefore are to take no notice of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>I anſwer in the firſt place, that ſuch that ſo reaſon, cannot free themſelves of horrible ſlighting the ſacred word of God, and derogating in a high degree from the excellency and authority of it: and I feare the guilt of this evill will one day lye heavy on their ſoules and conſciences, though now they make nothing of it. For if the contempt of Civill Lawes, and Statutes of earthly Princes and States, when they are printed and publiſhed for the better regulating of Common-wealths, and to which all are bound to yeeld ſubmiſſion and ſubjection, that there may be no Tyranny nor Anarchy; I ſay, if the caſting off of ſuch Lawes, and refuſing to ſquare their outward actions in civill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, to make our own wills our lawes to guide us, bee lookt upon as a matter ſo heynous, and deſervedly puniſht, what ſhall
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:165014:35"/>we conceive then will be the condition of thoſe that caſt off the Book of the Scriptures, wherein God hath ſet down his Lawes and Statutes to order all States and Common-wealths in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and men and women in particular, in their walking before God, as the Apoſtle faith, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25. <hi>If they eſcaped not, who refuſed him that ſpake on earth, much more ſhall not wee eſcape, if we turne away from him that ſpeaketh from heaven.</hi> And where is the voyce of God now from heaven, but in the ſacred Scriptures?</p>
            <p n="2">2. To lay aſide the Scriptures, and truſt meerly to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is not this a down-right ſeparating and dividing what GOD hath joyned together and made one? The Scriptures which are the very Word and Minde of God, have in every part of them, the Spirit, whereby they are quickned, and the Spirit is in them as light in the <hi>Sunne,</hi> and we may as eaſily ſeparate the <hi>light</hi> from the <hi>Sunne,</hi> as the <hi>Spirit</hi> from the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> For as the <hi>Sunne</hi> would ſoon ceaſe to be, if the light and heat were gone, or taken from it: ſo here, if the <hi>Spirit</hi> ſhould ceaſe from the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> they ſhould ceaſe to be the Word of God, which cannot be, in regard that Gods <hi>Word endureth for ever, Pſal.</hi> 119.89. and <hi>Mark</hi> 13.31.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the <hi>Scriptures</hi> muſt be laid aſide, and men truſt to the private Dictates of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> as they ſay, which way and how will they be able to confute thoſe that are unſound in the Faith? now will they ſtone<note n="*" place="margin">Lapidandi ſunt haeretici ſacrarum literarum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentis. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than. cont. Ari. or. 2.</hi>
               </note> Heretickes but by Arguments from the Scriptures? For others will as ſtrongly pretend to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and to receive from the <hi>Spirit</hi> what they hold, as thoſe that are found. <hi>e.g.</hi> If one ſhould come and preach ſalvation by the workes of the Law, or a mans own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſueſſe, and not by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, or of faith in Chriſt, and ſay, <hi>The Spirit perſwades him hereunto;</hi> who can contradict him, if there be no Scriptures or word of God writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, to ſhew him the minde of God to the contrary, but onely the ſecret and inward teaching of the Spirit? And ſo I might inſtance in many other particulars.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Beſides, what if you be deceived, (as nothing is more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain) and in ſtead of the teachings of <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> it be the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of your own deceitfull and corrupt heart, or the actings of <hi>that foule Spirit the Devill,</hi> that oftentimes changeth or tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes himſelfe <hi>into an Angel of light,</hi> on purpoſe to deceive?
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:165014:36"/>What then? Now how will you diſtinguiſh between the Dictates of the one and the other, except by this,<note n="*" place="margin">Hincotiam apparet impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ſententiae Libertinorum noſtri temporis qui ſe zelotas ſpiritus appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant. Quorum aliqui Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae ſacrae Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maticum &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuinum ſenſum zanquam literam oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentem ecclrſ. Nov. Teſt. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utilem conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt, &amp; neſcio quae pbanatica ſui cerebri ſomniaſub ſpiritus titulo bominibus conantur obtrudere. Haec ſenteneia falſa &amp; pernitioſa eſt, quia S. Script: neglecta nihil certi in religione Chri liana conſtitui poteſt, quum nullum <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> aut norma extra eam dari poſſit, quae à falſa perſuaſione, &amp; erroris efficacia, quam De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Evangelit contemptôribus tanquam juſtus Iudex ſaepe immittit, divinam veritatem diſtinguat; &amp; quia ſpiritus ſanctus non niſt per verbam extermon &amp; ſacram Scripturam in cordibus hominum ad ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem eſt efficax: nude &amp; Paulus ſuitm miniſterium, Miniſterium Spiritus appellat, <hi>2 Cor. 3. Vide Synop. pur. Theolog. p. 11. de S. Script. neceſſ.</hi>
               </note> that the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God</hi> never dictates any thing but what is agreeable unto, &amp; may be reſolved into the Scriptures, or t written word of <hi>God,</hi> but the other not. <hi>e.g.</hi> When a man is perſwaded that Chriſt is not God, as well as Man, that there is no reſurrection of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, nor reward nor puniſhment after this life, that ſin and grace are both equally of God, &amp;c. with a thouſand ſuch like abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; how ſhall a perſon diſcern that the perſwaſions he hath of theſe things, are not from the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> but from <hi>Satan</hi> and his owne wicked heart, but this, becauſe they are directly againſt what is revealed to us in the Scriptures<hi rend="sup">l</hi>, the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> never per ſwading any to ſuch things as he hath himſelf ſpoken againſt in the Word <hi>written.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Moreover, to what purpoſe did the holy Ghoſt make uſe of thoſe holy men of God (as the Prophets and Apoſtles are ſtiled) to be his <hi>Amanuenſes,</hi> or Scribes to write down and commit to paper, what the minde of the eternall God was, which he would have made known to the children of men, concerning their faith and obedience, if the Scriptures are of no more uſe to beleevers? Doubtleſſe the workes of God are not in vain, he made the two great lights in Heaven, the Sunne and Moon, the one to rule the Day, and the other the Night; now would it not be a weake, if nota wicked thing, for any to ſay, what need we any more the uſe of the Sunne or Moone, is not God himſelfe ſufficient? ſo here, is it not as weake, if not as wicked a thing to ſoy? What need is there of the Scriptures, when wee have the Spirit himſelfe to teach us?</p>
            <p>Beſides, doth not the Apoſtle affirme in the firſt to <hi>Timothy,</hi> that the Scriptures are exceeding uſefull and profitable for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, for reproofe, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:165014:36"/>unto all good workes, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17. And then to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi> That <hi>whatſoever is written, is written for our inſtruction, that we through patience and comfore of the Scriptures might have hope, Rom.</hi> 15.4. And doth not Chriſt himſelf ſay, that one chiefe cauſe why men erre from the truth, is, becauſe they are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the Scriptures? <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.29. And doth he not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo requite men to ſearch the Scriptures upon this ground, becauſe they teſtifie of him. Mark that well, <hi>They teſtifie,</hi> not ſimply the Spirit, but the Scriptures alſo, <hi>they beare witneſſe</hi> to Chriſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true and onely <hi>Meſſiah</hi> that ſhould come into the world, with many other pretious ends and uſes, to which the ſacred Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are uſefull and profitable, as were eaſie to produce, if need were.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But laſtly, to ſay no more, how doth this open a doore to all manner of abominations both in opinion and practice: for if every man muſt be left to the private teachings of the Spirit, and have no recourſe at all any longer to the ſacred Canon of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, what abominations will men and women ſtick to admit of, and beare off all with this. The Spirit leads me hereunto, I am taught by the Spirit, and perſwaded by the Spirit: ſo that if a man ſhould be ſtirred up to lay violent hands upon his neighbour (as I have heard a drunkard once did on one that was of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and baſted him to ſome tune; and being demanded by the party why he did ſo, he anſwered him (in his own language) hee could not help it, the Spirit moved him thereunto) and take away his purſe or his life from him; or a vile wretch ſhould attempt the deflouring of a virgin, or committing of any other abomination, and put all off with this, that the Spirit dictates ſuch things to him, &amp; he is under no law but that of the Spirit, would not this be dreadfull both to God and Man: and ſo for any damnable errors in judgement, that the Scriptures condemne to the pit of hell, and warn us to take heed of, as we defire to eſcape damnation, doth not this opinion make way to the entertaining of them, when people ſhall be perſwaded there is no uſe of the Scriptures to bee as a Rule to them to walk by, but they are to truſt onely to the inward dictates of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Beſides, if this ſhould be allowed of, that the Scriptures are of no luſe, but we muſt, truſt to the Spirit in all, what certainty then can there be in any point of Religion and faith, for every one will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve as the Spint dictates to him, and as many men, ſo there will
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:165014:37"/>be almoſt as many mindes. Nay further, what bottome will men and women have to build the foundneſſe of their opinions upon, and that it's not their meere fancie if they caſt away the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſeeing what they conceive to day to be the right, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row they may be perſwaded to be otherwiſe, if they truſt to what is ſpoken and dictated ſecretly to them: and where will your ſoules end, and fix a period in matters of opinion, when they once begin to take this courſe of caſting off the Scriptures? Doubtleſſe they cannot tell themſelves, there being a fathomleſſe depth in the pit of error, out of which poore creatures can never extricate themſelves, being once ſhut up in it. Bleſſed are thoſe ſoules, that are ſo taught of God in the Miniſtery of his Word and Spirit, as to feare comming nigh the brink of that pit.</p>
            <p>THus (Sirs) I have diſpatcht the Anſwers to the forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned grounds, what remaineth in the cloſe of all (leaving the ſucceſſe and iſſue of all to the Lord Jeſus) but that I adde one word to perſwade you, in the bowels of Chriſt, to conſider from whence you are fallen, and <hi>repent and doe your firſt workes, Rev.</hi> 2.4. before the Lord Jeſus be revealed from heaven againſt you. I cannot but apprehend your condition as very ſad, not only in reſpect of your ſin, but of your ſorrow that is like to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take you: For as ſure as the Lord liveth, all thoſe that refuſe to kiſſe the Sonne, and will not have him to rule over them, but doe what in them lies to break his<note n="*" place="margin">By bonds and cords is meant the diſcipline and government of Chriſt in his Church &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as the words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignify, Pſal. <hi>2.3.</hi> Now the lawes and ordinances of Chriſt, or his diſcipliue and government, are called bonds &amp; cords, not that they are ſo in themſelves, but becauſe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſo judge of them, looking upon them as ſo many fetters &amp; manacles that keep them from the enjoyment of their luſts and carnall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, which is the main cauſe of their enmitie againſt them, and rejecting of them.</note> bonds, and caſt his cords from them, ſhall periſh in the way of their rebellion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.12. and be brought forth and ſlain before him, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. You cannot be ignorant how jealous the eternall. God is of the honour of his Chriſt, and that he is now dealing with the great and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ones of the earth, for their ſlighting of him, and rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him: And why ſhould you be found in the number of them? you (I ſay) that have made profeſſion of him, and ſworne fealty to him? If ſuch ſhall have ſtripes that have not done their Maſters will, though they have been ignorant of it, what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thoſe then that have known it and yet have not done it, nay, wilfully neglected the doing of it? O conſider it betimes, for it's a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the living God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.31. If thoſe that deſpiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> law died without mercy, &amp;c. of how much ſorer puniſhment ſuppoſe yee ſhall they be thought worthy that trample under their feet the Sonne
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:165014:37"/>of God? &amp;c. Can you think that your profeſſion of holineſſe, and pretence of living in God, can beare you out while your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is clean contrary, uſing your liberty as an occaſion to the fleſh? O conſider whether you be not within the number of thoſe which are propheſied ſhall come in theſe latter days of the world in which we live.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Men that ſhall <hi>have a form of godlineſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The propheſie of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but denying the power thereof,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.5. <hi>that creep into houſes, and lead cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſilly women, laden with ſinnes, led away with divers luſts, ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> verſe 6.7. <hi>reſiſters of the truth, as</hi> Jannes <hi>and</hi> Jambres, <hi>men of corrupt mindes, reprobate concerning the faith, who ſhall proceed no further, for their folly ſhall be made manifeſt unto all men, as theirs alſo was,</hi> v. 8, 9.</item>
               <item>2. Men that <hi>deny the Lord that bought them,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.1.<note place="margin">The propheſie of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that walke after the fleſh in the luſt of uncleanneſſe, that deſpiſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, preſumptuous, ſelfe-willed, and who are not afraid to ſpeak evill of dignities,</hi> verſe 10. <hi>that count it pleaſure to ryot in the day time, and ſport themſelves with their own deceivings,</hi> v. 13. <hi>that have eyes full of adultery, not being able to ceaſe from ſinne, beguiling unſtable ſoules, whoſe hearts are exerciſed with covetous practices,</hi> verſ. 14. <hi>that have forſaken the right way, and are gone aſtray, following the wayes of Baalam the ſonne of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> verſe 15. <hi>that ſpeake great ſwelling words of vanity, and allure through the luſts of the fleſh, through much wantonneſſe, thoſe that were cleane eſcaped from them that live in error,</hi> v. 18. <hi>that promiſe them liberty, but in the meane while are themſelves ſervants of corruption, being overcome and brought into bondage,</hi> v. 19.</item>
               <item>3. Men that have a <hi>Spirit of Antichriſt in them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The propheſie of the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that goe out from the Affemblies, and communions of the Saints,</hi> 1 John 2. 18, 19. <hi>that deny that Jeſus is the Chriſt, that deny the Father and the Sonne,</hi> v. 22, 23. <hi>that will not acknowledge J. Chriſt. to be come in the fleſh,</hi> 1 John 4.3. <hi>that are of the world, that ſpeak of the world, and the world heareth them,</hi> v. 5. <hi>that are not of God, and therefore will not heare thoſe that are ſent of God, being led by the Spirit of error,</hi> v 6.</item>
               <item>4. Men that <hi>turn the grace of God into laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The propheſie of the Apoſtle <hi>Iude.</hi>
                  </note> Jude 4. <hi>that are filthy dreamers, defilers of the fleſh, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of dominion, and ſpeake evill of dignities,</hi> verſe. 8. <hi>that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:165014:38"/>corrupt themſelves as bruit beaſts in what they know naturally,</hi> v. 10. <hi>That goe in the way of Cain, and runne greedily after the error of Baalam for reward, and periſh in the gainſaying of Core.</hi> v. 11. <hi>That are ſpots in feaſts of charity, feeding without feare, that are cloudt without water, carried about of winds, trees whoſe fruit withereth, without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots,</hi> v. 12 <hi>That are raging waves of the ſea, foaming out their owne ſhame, wandring ſtarres, to whom is reſerved the blackneſſe of darkneſſe for ever,</hi> v. 13. with much more to this purpoſe, in v. 15, 16, 18. concluding all with this, that they are ſuch as<note n="*" place="margin">This place hath formerly been much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed by the Prelates and their crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſtill is by thoſe that have changed the Name, but not the Nature of them, applying it to ſuch as come out of Babylon, and from the mixtures and corruptions of man in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, to ſerve the Lord after his own minde and will, made known to them in the word, when the place is clean contrary to be underſtood and applied.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeparate themſelves, viz.</hi> from the true ordinances, &amp; from the comunion of the godly in the uſe of them, as may be gathered from the follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing verſes, 20, 21. <hi>being ſenſuall, having not the Spirit,</hi> v. 19.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Now whether ſuch as to this day (under a pretence of living in God, and enjoying Goſpel-liberty, doe caſt off the uſe of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, deny Churches miniſtery, &amp;c. and walk after the fleſh to the fulfilling of the luſts thereof, as they were wont to doe before they were firſt enlightned) be not ſuch as are before mentioned, I leave to any that are unprejudiced men to conſider.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to draw to a concluſion of all, in regard that the will of Chriſt is, that we ſhould <hi>have compaſſion on ſome, making a difference,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 22.</note> thereby teaching us, that ſome may erre out of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and others out of wilfulneſſe, and ſo are not to be dealt with in the ſame way and manner: I therefore in the laſt place humbly deſire in the greateſt meekneſſe, and bowels of compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſuch who have been carried away with this <hi>error</hi> of the wicked (to renounce and caſt off the uſe of ordinances, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of duties which Jeſus Chriſt hath commanded to be performed) out of <hi>weakneſſe</hi> and <hi>infirmity,</hi> would be intreated <hi>timely</hi> to conſider the evil of ſuch a courſe and practiſe, how much it derogates from the honour of Chriſt, and happineſſe of their own ſouls, <hi>Deare ſouls</hi> for whom Chriſt died, and to whom Chriſt hath (poſſibly) many times made known the kindneſſe of his heart, I beſeech you weigh the former <hi>Conſiderations</hi> without prejudice, and then tell me whether you are not out of the way. Conſider the anſwers to the ſeverall grounds, upon which you
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:165014:38"/>build the leaving off the practice of duties and ordinances, and then ſee whether you have not cauſe to ſit down with <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and ſmite on the thigh, and ſay every one to himſelfe, <hi>What have I done? what an evill and bitter thing is this, that I have caſt off the wayes and meanes in which I formerly enjoyed ſuch ſoule-ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying, raviſhing, melting communion with the Lord Jeſus, and the Father through him.</hi> 
               <q>Pray give me leave to demand ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly of you, whether it was not farre better with your ſoules, when you kept cloſe with God in the uſe of ordinances, and were ſtrict in cloſet converſes with your beloved, whether ſin were not more irkſome, tedious, grievous, but then ſome to your ſouls, then now it is? whether the Saints were not more amiable in your eyes then now they are, &amp; comunion w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> them in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er &amp;c. a little corner of heaven in your apprehenſion? &amp; the ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of the wicked more loathſome? whether you were not more tender in your conſciences concerning the commiſſion of ſin, and more afraid of diſhonoring God, then now you be? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you were not more carried out and enlarged in doing of good, more ſpirituall in your walking, talking, affecting, acting, then now you are, more humble in your own eyes, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full over your owne hearts, making conſcience of all your thoughts, words and wayes;</q> whereas now you thinke there is no neceſſity of ſuch ſtrictneſſe, though the holy Ghoſt tells us, that as he that hath called us is holy, ſo ought we to be holy, and that in all manner of converſation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15, 16.</p>
            <p>Now I beſeech you, deare ſoules conſider, can that poſſibly be the way of truth, the way to glory, that renders you worſe then you have been, more unholy, unſpirituall, uncircumſpect, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to Chriſt, then you were wont to be? I beſeech you deale plainly and impartially with your own ſoules; Don't you begin to find a change in your ſelves, in reſpect of the former par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars? &amp; you can now diſpenſe with the duties of your relations both towards God and man, which formerly you could not in the leaſt doe. Now I pray conſider, can theſe things ſtand with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons living in God? Can living in God and living in ſin ſtand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether? Can the Ark and <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agon</hi> ſtand together? O that ever Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan ſhould thus beguile any of your pretious ſoules. In my weake apprehenſion, the higher a perſon lives in God, the more holy he is the more like to God, the more crucified to ſin and the world, the leſſe deſirous of liberty to the fleſh, the more ſtudious of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:165014:39"/>thoſe things that are pleaſing &amp; acceptable unto God, through Jeſus Chriſt. And whereas many talk of their liberty which they have above others, when they have caſt off all duties and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances to live in God: I would fain know whether that liberty be not a lawleſſe liberty, and whether the excellency of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an can poſſibly lie in it, or wheter living in God can ſtand with ſuch a liberty. If to live in God be to take liberty to thinke, and ſpeak, and doe as we our ſelves liſt, and to be without all check and controll in our way, both of God and Man; then wee may caſt away the Scriptures in deed, and all religion, and every one walk after the imagination of his own heart. But, deare ſoules, be no longer led away with ſuch deceivings and deceivers, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you liberty, but in the mean time are <hi>ſervants to corruption</hi> themſelves, and are overcome and brought into bondage, and ſeek to doe the ſame by you. O hearken no longer to their <hi>Syren-like Songs,</hi> but bow your eares to the voyce of Jeſus Chriſt, crying to you, <hi>Return, return, repent, repent, and doe your firſt workes, for I am married to you, I am loath the death of ſinners; why will you wilfully caſt away your pretious ſoules? Though you have dealt unkindly with me, and forgotten thoſe ſweet embracings you formerly enjoyed from me, when you made conſcience of the duties of my ſervice and worſhip, yet return, return, for I am a God that delighteth to ſhew mercy, and whom mercy pleaſeth: though you have in ſome meaſure denied my Name; and been aſhamed to own it before the Heathen, yet repent and doe your firſt works, and I will take you and bring you to my holy mountain, and you ſhall goe no more out and I will write upon you the Name of my God, and the name of the citie of my God, which is new Jeruſalem, which commeth down out of heaven from my God; and I will write upon you my new Name.</hi> Now the ſame bleſſed God, and our Saviour, that ſpake theſe words, ſet home theſe things upon your hearts, and make them effectuall for that end for which they were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:165014:39"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of thoſe (never enough to be abhorred opinions) that ſome of thoſe more eſpecially that caſt off and renounce the uſe of Goſpel-ordinances, doe profeſſedly hold and maintain.</head>
            <list>
               <item>FIrſt, There's no God nor Devill, Heaven nor Hell, but what is within us.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> There is no truth nor power in the Word, but as it is made out ſo to my Spirit: <hi>i.</hi> the Spirit ſpeakes it ſo within me.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> The ſayings and wrtings of the Prophets and Apoſtles in the Scriptures, and of other Saints, are of equal value and truth, becauſe by the ſame Spirit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> There are many ſilly, vain, groſſe, and contrary things in the Scriptures; poore men they ſpeake according to the preſent temper of their Spirits.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> There may be, and ſome are, above the profiting power of the miniſtery of the Word, and uſe of the Scriptures.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> There is no ſin in the Saints, they are under no law but that of the Spirit, which is freedome.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> There is no ſinne againſt GOD, For wee cannot reach him.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> That Gods dealings with all, good and bad, are in love, for God is love.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> There is no ſtate after this life, but (at that which is called Death) all good and bad are ſwallowed up of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> That ſinne and grace are equally of God, and agreeth to his will.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> That all perſons and things, act and are acted as God will have them.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:165014:40"/>
                  <hi>12</hi> That whatſoever men can that they doe, and in all according to Gods will.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> That there is no reſurrection of the body, nor reward or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment after this life.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> That there may be as much of God ſeen and enjoyed in any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile labour, as in the Miniſtery of the Word, Prayer, &amp;c. and that they have more.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> As for that men call worſhip of God, conſcience, &amp;c. they know not what it meanes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> That ſolemne Religious duties in publick or private, are but formes, bodily exerciſes, meerly Legall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> That men may as well work or play on the Lords day, as on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other; And as for them (to whom God is departed out of Ordinances, and abundantly anſwers another way) it is better.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> That the ſoule is the breath of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19</hi> That it is the Saints priviledge to be one Spirit, and therefore ſee no reaſon why there may not bee a community in all things.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20</hi> That none can be certain whether he be in the truth or error, but themſelves; becauſe depending upon the teaching of the Spirit, yet they themſelvs ſoes not knowing what they ſhall hold for the future.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21</hi> That they cannot joyn in prayer with others, becauſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of wants, ſinnes, drawing neere to GOD, and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions for the Lords preſence, giving out of help, &amp;c. with which they cannot cloſe, becauſe denying the firſt, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the latter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22</hi> That as for wantonneſſe, licentiouſneſſe, Libertiniſme, and turning grace into wantonneſſe, taking occaſions from mercy to ſin, &amp;c. they know not what you mean, they are not incident to Saints.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23</hi> That they will, and think they ought to follow their light, though they are to loſe heaven and gain hell preſently for it (if there be ſuch things.)</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24</hi> That ſuch as are one in the Spirit of love, it is a great wrong for any to hinder their union and communion in any thing.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25</hi> That what men call <hi>Baſtardy,</hi> is onely upon the account of the
<pb facs="tcp:165014:40"/>men of the world, who marry and are called <hi>Baſtards,</hi> Heb. <hi>12.</hi> not with God, with whom Saints are as Angels in community, Luke <hi>20.34, 35, 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26</hi> That they have already for Spirituals what they expect, and lack nothing, and act Faith onely for Corporall ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>27</hi> That what the Saints (becauſe of others baſeneſſe and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe doe now in ſecret, they ſhall doe openly, <hi>Matth. 20.26, 27.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28</hi> That there is nothing fleſhly or carnall in the Saints perſons or actings, but all ſpirituall and holy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29</hi> That there is no Trinity of Perſons in the Godhead.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30</hi> That there is no diſtinction between God ana Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>31</hi> That all are born without ſin, and Saints live without ſin.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32</hi> That a Saint may out-live all his religion, all ties upon his conſcience, and yet remain a Saint.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:165014:41"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A true Copy of a Letter from</hi> Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth, February the <hi>12.</hi> Relating the manner of Gods working upon one that had caſt off the uſe of Duties and Ordinances, ſent by an approved and known godly man that was an Eye-witneſſe.</head>
            <p>I Have onely one thing to tell you, and 'tis a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable paſſage of Divine Providence: There is one <hi>Nicholas Earle,</hi> a Shoomaker, ſometimes of <hi>Tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and now a Souldier in the Fort, who having with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this moneth given way to the ſtudying of eſtranging himſelfe from God, conceiving that there was no need of Miniſters, but that they muſt down; Sacraments but Ceremonies, Sabbaths not to be kept, and thereupon was reſolved to open his windowes the laſt Sabbath, and to that end diſputed and argued with ſome about it the Saturday, and then charged his wife not to teach his children prayers, or Duties, or Commandements; and my man <hi>George</hi> being preſent, ſaw him in his hot conteſtation fall to the ground roaring and crying, and taking deep deteſtation againſt thoſe that bare the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God, commending himſelfe onely a Saint, and others out of the way. He was againſt ſinging, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that when the Souldiers in their daily duties in the Fort ſang, he ſpake to them and ſaid, they did lye like Devils. The man that Saturday night was under deep temptations, ſtrange apparitions, the Devill ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to appeare to him, with ſtrange roaring. The Sabbath day he ſent for me; and when I came, at firſt
<pb facs="tcp:165014:41"/>ſight I was welcome, but ſuddenly I was loathſome, and he ſpat in defiance of me. I ſaw him in that temper and fit, I left him: But the munday about Noone the man came to himſelfe, hath a ſtrange conviction of his error; whereas before he left giving of thankes, before and after the receiving of the creatures, now he is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at the thoughts of it, acknowledging his error. I have had conference with him, and he cannot be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full enough that God hath ſo ſoone returned him: He deſires the Miniſters to bleſſe God for his return, and pray that he may be ſtedfaſt. This I write as certaine, and that you may acquaint others to take heed how profeſſedly they keep out of Gods way: he wiſheth all his friends to take warning by it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
